<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="work" xml:lang="en" xml:id="LIT4050ZenaBul">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Vita of Saint Bula surnamed ʾAbib</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t2">ገድሉ፡ ለአባ፡ ቡላ።</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t2" type="normalized">Gadla ʾabbā Bulā</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t3">ዜና፡ ለአብ፡ ክቡር፡ ወትሩፈ፡ ትጋህ፡ አባ፡ ቡላ፡ ዝውእቱ፡ አቢብ፡</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t3" type="normalized">Zenā la-ʾab kǝbur wa-tǝrufa tǝgāh ʾabbā Bulā zǝ-wǝʾǝtu ʾAbib</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p>
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Work of the literatures of Ethiopia and Eritrea</p>
         </sourceDesc>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness corresp="BNFet132#ms_i2"/>
               <witness corresp="BAVet32#ms_i3"/>
               <witness corresp="BLorient702#ms_i3"/>
               <witness corresp="BLorient711#ms_i2"/>
               <witness corresp="BLorient694#ms_i1"/>
               
               <witness corresp="BNFabb110">BNA 110: 20 = BNAC 110: 17 = BNACR 164: 17 (XVIII s.): ff. 151r-157rb (25 Ṭeqemt); Malkǝʾ ff. 157rb-158rc; Salām ff. 157rb-158rc</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML1479">EMML 1479: 16 (1459-60): ff. 111ra-116va (25 Ṭeqemt)</witness>
               <witness type="external" corresp="http://gundagunde.digital.utsc.utoronto.ca/islandora/object/gundagunde%3A94747/contact#page/1/mode/2up"></witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p>(the Synaxary version) On this day died Abba Bula, who was surnamed ʾAbib. The name of the father of this holy
               man was Abraham, and that of his mother was Harik, and they were natives of the country
               of Rome, and came from the borders of Lupi; and since there was a persecution in the days
               of the Emperor Maximianus they continued to fly from city to city. As they lacked a son
               they entreated God, with fasting and prayer, to give them a son. And the angel of the Lord
               appeared unto them in a dream, and gave them a vine cluster which was full of grapes, and
               when the blessed woman conceived, a large tree which was near their house blossomed,
               and on the leaves thereof were written in the language of Rome the following words: 
               “Bula servant of God, and the saint of the God of Jacob, Who dwelleth in Zion.” And
               when the child was born they left him for some time without making him a Christian.
               Then our Lady Mariyam appeared unto the Archbishop of Rome, and commanded him to
               go to the house of Abraham and baptize the child; and when he arrived there he made him
               a Christian and called his name “Bula.” When the father and the mother of the child heard
               [this] they marveled because he had called the child by that name without their having told
               him the name. When the archbishop had prayed, bread for the Offering and a cup of wine
               came down from heaven, and he consecrated them and administered unto them the Holy
               Mysteries. When the boy was one year old he spoke plainly and said, “One is the Holy
               Father, One is the Holy Son, One is the Holy Ghost.” After a little [time] his father and his
               mother died, on the sixteenth day of the month of Hedar (Nov-Dec). When the boy was
               ten years of age there arrived a wicked governor who ordered [the people] to worship idols,
               and when Abba Bula heard about it, he went to the governor and cursed his filthy idols.
               When the governor saw the small stature of the boy he marveled greatly. And he
               commanded [his soldiers] to drive nails into him, and to scrape his body, and to strip off
               his skin, and to saw off his hands and his feet, and to beat his back with whips, and to cast
               him on the wheel among the sharp knives and spikes, and to drag him along the road of the
               city; [and they did so]. And Saint Michael came and saved him, and healed him. Then
               Bula went to another wicked governor and reviled him, and the governor was wroth with
               him and cut off his head with the sword, and he was crowned on the eighteenth day of the
               month of Miyazya (April-May). And Saint Michael came down from heaven and raised
               him up unharmed, and he took him into the desert, and he arrayed him in the garb of the
               monk, and put upon him a mark in appearance like the sign of the Cross, and he said unto
               him, “God hath commanded thee to be a companion of the Saints.” And Abba Bula went
               up into a dry (i.e., withered) tree, and he dwelt therein fighting incessantly, and whenever
               he remembered the Crucifixion of our Lord Jesus Christ and His Passion, he always cast
               himself down from the top of the tree. One day having cast himself down Satan was
               strong to kill him, and he died, but our Redeemer came straightway and raised him up, and
               he said unto him, “Thy name shall not be ‘Bula’ only, but ‘ ʾAbibha,’ for thou shalt
               become many fathers.” And Bula loved Christ more and more, and he was always beating
               his face, and cutting his flesh with knives, every member of him, and he beat his back with
               seven hundred stripes; through these acts he died three times and our Redeemer raised him
               up again. And on each occasion He showed him how he had been born of a virgin, and on
               other days He showed him how he was seized by the Jews and His Passion. And for this
               reason Bula lived without eating and without drinking for two and forty years, and he
               never lay on his side for six and sixty years. And he also kept his head fixed for twelve
               years and six months, until his brains perished. One day when he saw the Passion of our
               Lord, he place a sword upright before him and then fell upon it and died. And our Lady
               Mariyam came with angels to the place where his body was, and she said unto him, “Peace
               be unto thee, O my beloved”; and his body spoke and said unto her, “Peace be unto thee, O
               Queen of the world.” And she laid her hands upon his body and healed him. And when
               his days were ended, and it was time for him to depart from this world, our Lord Jesus
               Christ appeared unto him having in His hands shining crowns set with gems of various
               kinds, and shining raiment. And He said unto him, “Come unto Me, O My beloved ʾAbib,
               so that thou mayest enjoy never-ending pleasure. I swear unto thee by Myself that
               whosoever calleth upon thy name I will forgive him his sins. And whosoever
               commemorates thee, or show mercy on the poor, or clothes the naked, or feedeth the
               hungry, or gives drink to the thirsty man, or buildeth a shrine for thee, or writes the story of 
               thy strife, or readeth it or heareth it, I will forgive his sins even to the tenth generation.”
               Having said this He kissed his mouth, and bearing him upon His breast carried him up into
               the air. And when he heard the praise of the angels, his soul tore itself away from his
               body, and entered the heavenly Jerusalem. Salutation to ʾAbib.
               Salutation to the twelve handmaidens, and to the three and forty men, and to the three
               hundred and sixty women, who under the influence of ʾAbib became martyrs. </p>
         </abstract>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language></langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-11-17">Created XML record from Ethio authority google spreadsheet</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2016-11-30">Title updated and witness added</change>
         <change who="MV" when="2016-12-20">Witnesses added</change>
         <change who="DR" when="2017-03-29">Added keywords</change>
         <change who="SG" when="2019-03-28">Added keywords</change>
         <change when="2022-01-06" who="ES">added content biblio witnesses</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <div type="edition">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:id="Introduction" xml:lang="gez">
               <label>Introduction</label>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:id="MainPart" xml:lang="gez">
               <label>Main Part</label>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="hymn" xml:id="hymn">
              <label>hymn</label>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listRelation>
               <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT4050ZenaBul" passive="PRS1246AbibBu"/>
               <relation name="ecrm:CLP46i_may_form_part_of" active="LIT4050ZenaBul" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
            </listRelation>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>