<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="work" xml:lang="en" xml:id="LIT4510GadlaBa">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Vita and Martyrdom of ʾAbbā Baʾamin</title>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
            <editor key="DR"/>
            <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p>
                This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Work of the literatures of Ethiopia and Eritrea</p>
         </sourceDesc>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness corresp="BerOr117">BerlD 66: 5 [Or. fol. 117] (XIV-XV s.): pp. 131a-143b (p. 131a: 9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>                             
               <witness corresp="BLorient687">BL Or. 687-688 = BLW 258: 31 (XVIII s.): ff. 160ra-161vc (f. 160r: 9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML1479">EMML 1479: 34 (1459-60): ff. 251r-254r (9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML6903">EMML 6903: 19 (XV s.): ff. 106va-108v (f. 106v: 9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML6965">EMML 6965: 28 (XIV s.): ff. 165va-167rb (f. 165v: 9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>
               <witness corresp="Tanasee121">Ṭānāsee 121 = Dāgā Esṭifānos 10: 26 (1416): A: IV: 4: ff. 169ra-171rb (f. 169r: 9 Tāḫśāś)</witness>
               <witness corresp="HamDabraLibanosGS">Dabra Libānos (XV s.) 29</witness>
               <witness corresp="BerOr9486">Staatsbibliothek Preussischer Kulturbesitz (Berlin), Hs. or. 9486 = ÄHS 175, Fragment Aeth. 1, Privatbe-sitz E. Hammerschmidt: 2 (XIV s.): f. 2ra-vb (framm.): 
               ÄHS p. 379 "Das Fragment gehört zu jenen der Hss. Ṭānāsee 92 (II), 105 (I) und 110 (I) [vgl. VOHD XX 2, 121f, 151f. und 161f.], alles Handschriften von Rēmā, wo sie als Deckblätter für andere Handschriften verwendet worden sind"  </witness>             
               
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract><p>(from the Synaxary version) This holy man was from the monastery of the sons of Khadhib, to the
            north of the province of ‘Eshmunayn, in the country of Egypt, and from the city of Tersa;
            he was the steward of a certain rich man, and was beloved by everybody because of his
            sincerity and justice. And the rich man had a wife who loved ʾAbbā Baʾamin, and she
            trusted him greatly. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin pondered about the end of the world, and
            he left the service of that rich man, and he went to a monastery in that [place] and became
            a monk therein. When the rich man heard that ʾAbbā Baʾamin had left him, and departed,
            he was exceedingly sorry. And taking his wife with him he went unto him, “We cannot
            part from thee by any means, and we will not let thee go.” And the saint said unto them, “I
            cannot [return], I have vowed myself to God”; and they departed from him sorrowing
            greatly because of their parting from him. And this holy man fought a great and a good
            fight, and he lived a life of strenuous devotion to God for many years with fasting, and
            prayer, and vigil. And this was not enough for him, for he wished to become a martyr and
            to pour out his blood for the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ. And he went to the city of
            Antinoe where he found many Christians suffering torture, and he confessed our Lord
            Jesus Christ, and they inflicted severe tortures upon him, and they scourged him, and they
            burnt his body with fire, and they chopped off his limbs, and threw him on the wheel, and
            they made iron rods red-hot and burnt his flesh with them. And under all these tortures our
            Lord Christ strengthened him, and raised him up whole and uninjured. And whilst he was
            suffering in this wise the worship of idols came to an end, for Constantine the Just became
            emperor, and he commanded the keepers of the prisons to set free the Christians who had
            been shut up in the prison houses by the infidel Diocletian for the sake of Christ’s Name.
            And our Lord Jesus Christ appeared unto Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin and commanded him to go
            unto all those saints who were in prison, and to make them to know that our lord Christ
            reckoned among the martyrs those who were called “Confessors”; and the Emperor
            Constantine commanded [his servants] to bring seventy-two of them. And there was there
            with them Abba Nob, the confessor, and they went to him. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin
            dwelt in a monastery which was outside the city of ‘Eshmunayn, and God give him a great
            gift, and he healed the sick, and the report of him was noised abroad in all countries. Now
            a very severe illness came upon the empress, the wife of the Emperor of Rome, and it
            happened because of a certain God-fearing deacon who was near her, and who used to read
            to her every day the Book of the Vision of John the Evangelist, that is to say,
            “Abukalamsis (i.e. the Apocalypse).” And one of the emperor’s stewards was jealous of
            him and he went to the emperor and said unto him, “Know, O my lord, that John the
            deacon lieth with our lady the empress, thy wife, and maketh the pretence of reading to her
            the Book of the Vision of John every day.” When the emperor heard this he was very
            sorry, and he rose up straightway and went into his palace where the empress was, and he
            found the deacon standing before the empress and reading the Book of the Vision of John.
            And the emperor commanded [his soldiers] to take the deacon and his book and to sink
            them both in the river; and two men saw the form of a shining man descending, and he
            came and snatched the deacon out of the river together with his book, and he took him and
            placed him on an island; and when the two men saw this they marveled exceedingly, and 
            they went to their houses and told no one connected with the emperor what they had seen.
            When the empress saw what they had done to that deacon she was exceedingly sorry, and
            her illness increased, and the disease attacked her belly; and she continued to suffer from
            this disease for five and twenty years. And many physicians came to her but they were
            unable to heal her of her sickness. And a certain learned man counseled her, saying, “If
            thou wert to go to the holy men who are in the land of Egypt, then thou wouldst be healed
            of thy sickness and tribulation.” And straightway she rose up, and there were many
            soldiers with her, and she arrived in the land of Egypt, and she went about and visited
            many monasteries and churches, but she was not healed of her sickness. When she came to
            the city of Antinoe the nobles who saw her marveled exceedingly concerning her coming,
            and she told them everything about her sickness, and they counseled her to go to Saint
            ʾAbbā Baʾamin; and she embarked in a ship for the monastery of Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin.
            And one told the saint, saying, “Behold, the empress hath come to thee, and wishes to be
            blessed by thee.” And he said unto him, “What have I to do with the empress of the earth
            and her greatness?” And the brethren besought him earnestly to go out to her, and he did
            so; and when the empress saw him she bowed low at his feet. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin
            prayed concerning her sickness over some oil, and he anointed her therewith, and she was
            healed of her sickness. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin said unto her, “Knew thou that this
            sickness which hath come upon thee is caused by the deacon whom the emperor drowned
            in the river, but he is alive at this day and dwells on this island in the river, and the Book of
            the Vision of John Abukalamsis is with him”; and when the empress heard these words she
            marveled exceedingly, and she praised God and rejoiced with very great joy because the
            deacon was alive. And she offered to Saint Baʾamin much money and many gifts, but he
            took nothing from her except money [sufficient to buy] sacred vessels for the church, a
            paten, a chalice, and a cross of gold; then she returned to the city of Rome praising God.
            And when she met the emperor she told him all that had happened to her, and how Saint
            ʾAbbā Baʾamin had told her that the deacon whom he had drowned was alive at that time;
            and when the emperor heard this he marveled exceedingly and sent messengers to the
            island, and they found the deacon alive, and the Book of the Vision of John was with him;
            and they returned and reported this to the emperor. And the emperor sent a messenger to
            him a second time to entreat him to come to him; and they brought him to the emperor; and
            when the emperor saw him he rejoiced with very great joy, and bowed down at his feet,
            and he said unto him, “Forgive me my sin which I committed against thee.” And the saint
            said unto him, “May God forgive both of us our sins.” And after this that deacon was
            appointed Archbishop of the city of Rome, and he translated the Vision of John
            Abukalamsis. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin fought by day and by night, ceaselessly, the
            spiritual fight. And there was near him a certain holy bishop who made a festival of the
            martyrs, with several believers, in a certain monastery; and the Arian heretics took to
            themselves a false bishop and led astray very many of the people, and the bishop of the
            city came to Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin and told him of his sorrow [which was caused] by those
            heretics. When the festival of the martyrs arrived ʾAbbā Baʾamin prayed and entreated
            God, and prostrated himself with his people that He would make the counsel of the heretics
            void. Then he took a palm rod in his hand, and all the monks who were with him took
            each his palm rod in his hand, and they went to the place where the heretics were, and
            drove them away, and God, the Glorious and Most High, made void their counsel, and they
            have not returned to this day. And Saint ʾAbbā Baʾamin, being an aged man, fell sick of a mortal
            disease. And he gathered together the brethren and commanded them, and comforted
            them, and told them that [the end of] his days was near, and that he was going to God, and             
            the fathers and the brethren sorrowed because of his [approaching] separation from them,
            and then he delivered up his soul to God his Creator. And the brethren swathed him for
            burial in costly cloths and they sang psalms, and hymns, and dirges over him, as was meet.
            And his body was a help unto all those who came to it, or to the church, in the True Faith,
            and what they asked for came to them. Salutation to ʾAbbā Baʾamin who lay on a red-hot
            iron bed. </p></abstract>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#ethioauthlist">
               <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DR" when="2017-02-16">Created file</change>
         <change who="MV" when="2017-04-06">Added relation</change>
         <change who="ES" when="2022-01-05">Added content relation witnesses</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listRelation>
               <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT4510GadlaBa" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
               
               <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT4510GadlaBa" passive="PRS13684Baamin"/>
            </listRelation>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>