<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6537Besoy" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="n1">ገድለ፡ ብሶይ፡</title>
                    <title xml:lang="gez" type="normalized" corresp="#n1">Gadla Bǝsoy</title>
                <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#n1">Combat of Bishoy</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="ES"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness corresp="BLorient692">BL Or. 692 = BLW 256: 14 (XV s.): ff. 174ra-202vb (mutilous)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML6694">EMML 6694: 11 (XX s.): ff. 145va-149vb (3 Gǝnbot) [?]; with <ref type="work" corresp="LIT6542MirBesoy">Miracles</ref> 12 (XX s.): ff. 150ra-159r</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML7602">EMML 7602: 3 (1382-1413): ff. 39ra-56ra Besoy (f. 39r: 7 Ḥamlē)</witness>
                   
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p>(Synaxary version) This holy man came from Upper Egypt, from the city of ‘Akhim (Akhmim). In the days of his early
                    manhood he used to do works of abomination, and to eat and drink luxuriously. When
                    God chose him He brought upon him a severe illness, and he well-nigh died and delivered
                    up his spirit, and He showed him the places of punishment, and the great deep pits of hell,
                    and he saw men clothed in shining apparel, and in their hands they had the body of a man
                    which they tore into four pieces. And they said unto Besoy, “Thus will they do unto every
                    man who stealeth the possessions of men.” When he heard this word he was sorrowful in
                    his heart, and he wept a bitter weeping, and his soul returned to his body, and he lifted up
                    his eyes to heaven and said, “O my Lord and God, if Thou wilt heal me of this sickness, I
                    will repent of this my sin, and I will worship Thee with all my heart, and from this time
                    forward I will never look at a woman again.” And straightway God healed him of his
                    sickness, and he rose up and went to Dabra Banwayet, and the monks counseled him, and
                    they arrayed him in the garb of the monk. And he fought a great fight with fasting, and
                    prayer, and vigils for many years, until his fame was heard of throughout Egypt; and he
                    excelled among many saints, and he composed many Homilies and Admonitions, and
                    Teachings for the monks and for the laity. And he fasted a month at a time, and neither ate
                    bread nor drank water; and continued to fight the fight in this manner for a period of five
                    and thirty years. And he used to stand up all night in prayer. And the works of men were
                    manifest before him, whether righteous or sinners; and after this he became a little sick and
                    he died in peace. </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Hagiography"/>
                    <term key="Translation"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2022-01-07">Created entity</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="editions">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Colin2002Bsoy"/></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Bausi2004Bsoy"/></bibl>
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Beylot1986Bisoy"/></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:CLP46i_may_form_part_of" active="LIT6537Besoy" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6537Besoy" passive="PRS12651Pishoy"></relation>
                    
                </listRelation>
            </div><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>