<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6993MMDZMonk" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">Miracle of Mary: Dabra Zamaddo's Abbot Abuna Yohannǝs and how the monks revolted against him</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">206-207</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>At Dabra Zamaddo, the monks grew arrogant and came to despise the order of Abbuna Yohannes. Disturbed and saddened by the monks’ revolt, Abbuna Yohannes confided in Mary regarding the oppression he faced. He also explained that since she was the impartial ruler of everyone at the monastery, she must decide what to do. Mary then sent a pestilence to the monastery, and forty of the monks died within a week. Abba Benyami, who lived in Garagara, witnessed the destructiveness of the pestilence and warned Abbuna Yohannes to pray to Mary and save the remaining monks. Abbuna Yohannes started rogation, and every day for twelve days he carried a big rock on his head and toured the shrine. At the end of this period, the pestilence waned. Mary also came to Abbuna Yohannes with a message for the remaining monks. The message was that the Arami would come to destroy all Christians and their churches, and that the only hope of survival would be to flee.
                    
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1010</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">201-202</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1010</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT6993MMDZMonk" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT6993MMDZMonk" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1010"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6993MMDZMonk" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 127v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ ሎቱ፡ ለአቡነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ ሶበ፡ ተዐበዩ፡ ሰብአ፡ ደብር፡ ወአስተሐቀሩ፡ ቃሎ፡ ተሀውከ፡ ወሐዘነ፡ በልቡናሁ፡ ጥቀ፡ በእንተ፡ ሥርዓት፡ በዘኮነ፡ ከዊኖ፡ ሶበ፡ ይምዕዶሙ፡ ወይኤዝዞሙ፡ ይትዐደዉ፡ ቃሎ። አሜሃ፡ የሐዝን፡ ወይቴክዝ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">206-207</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013.</note>
                
                
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Lady Mary worked for Abuna Yohannǝs: When the people of the monastery became arrogant and despised his order, he was disturbed and was saddened in his heart very much. When he admonished them and gave them orders, following the rule whenever anything happened, they would violate his command. At that time he would be sad and depressed. A long time passed as they wrangled this way. And they lived a long time not observing what he told them. When the thickness of their hearts was too much, he started to tell his Lady of their violation and the oppression he suffered. The statement of his words ran like this: “If I am unable to keep them and if their hearts are not pleased with my words, you do what you want. You brought me here formerly and appointed me over them while my heart never thought of an appointment. However, at that time, they accepted me with pleasure; and they accepted me unanimously. But now they made their hearts evil. You judge me and them, because you are impartial, and you know the demeanor of all. What else shall I say?” And Our Lady, since she knew his oppression and the arrogance of the people of the monastery, sent pestilence to the people of the monastery. Forty monks died in one week. When Abba Bǝnyami saw, living in Garagara, by the grace of God, that the pestilence was sent, he sent a message to Abuna Yohannǝs, saying, “Pray for them to God and to Our Lady Mary, lest your remaining children be finished, because Our Lady and Our Lord Jesus Christ are angry because of your oppression”. When Abuna Yohannǝs heard, he started rogation, carrying a big rock on his head and touring the shrine twelve times every day. Within twelve days, the wrath of God receded. The remainder of his children was saved by the prayer of Our Lady Mary. For whoever goes to her does not suffer; and whoever trusts in her will not be ashamed. Regarding this, Abuna Yohannǝs finished his time trusting in her, undefeated by his enemies. And on the day of his rest, she revealed to him words of prophecy. He reported (them) to his children, saying to them, “The Aramis will come and destroy all the Christians and lay all the churches waste. You will not oppose them; you will not be able to (even if you want) because they are authorized by God. Only flee peradventure you will be saved”. He said this and rested from the toil of this world by the prayer of Our Lady Mary. May her prayer and blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be a buffer and shield for us on the day of trial and inquisition forever and ever. A(men)</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>