<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6939GadlaSosenna" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">ገድለ፡ ሶስና፡</title>
                <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t1" type="normalized">Gadla Sosǝnnā</title>
                <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1">Life of Susanna</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="CH"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
                    <listWit>
                        <witness corresp="TAfait008"/>
                    </listWit>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p>The text belonging to the Beta ʾƎsrāʾel (Ethiopian Jewish) literature. It is a renarration of the biblical story in
                    <ref type="work" corresp="LIT3194Susanna"/> , with Daniel replaced by Michael. It stands in close relation to the Christian 
                    <ref type="work" corresp="LIT3966Homily"/>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="BetaEsraelLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Hagiography"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="CH" when="2024-02-23">Created entity</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6939GadlaSosenna" passive="PRS11599Susanna"/>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6939GadlaSosenna" passive="PRS7049Michael"/>
                    <relation name="saws:isRelatedTo" active="LIT6939GadlaSosenna" passive="LIT3194Susanna"/>
                    <relation name="saws:isRelatedTo" active="LIT6939GadlaSosenna" passive="LIT3966Homily"/>
                </listRelation>
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Stenhouse1995Susanna"/></bibl>
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Wurmbrand1963Susanna"/></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div><!---->
            <div type="edition" resp="PRS10174Wurmbra">
                <note>The following text and translation is taken from 
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Wurmbrand1963Susanna"/><citedRange>29-34</citedRange></bibl>.</note>
                <ab xml:lang="gez">ይትባረክ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ አምላክ፡ እስራኤል፡ ዛቲ፡ መጽሐፈ፡ ድርሳን፡ ዘአውጽአ፡ እማኢየሩሳሌም፡ ከመ፡ ይነግር፡ ዕዮሙ፡ ወከብሮሙ፡ ወሢማቶሙ፡ 
                    ወሕይወቶሙ፡ ለሚካኤል፡ ወገብሬል፡ ወለእሎንቱ፡ ፬፡ እንሰሳ፡ ፳፬፡ ካህናተ፡ ሰማይ፡ <gap reason="ellipsis"/>ወኢሰማዕክሙኑ፡ ወኢርኢክሙኑ፡ ለሱስና፡፡ አቡሃ፡ 
                    ንጉሥ፡ ወእማኒ፡ ንግሥት፡ ወምታኒ፡ ንጉሥ፡፡ ወእምድኅረ፡ ሞተ፡ ምታ፡ እምጽኡ፡ ለአቡሃ፡ ነገሥት፡ ሐፄሃ፡ ወርቅ፡ ወብሩር፡ ወወሀቤዎ፡ ለአቡሃ፡ ወይሌልዎ፡ ሀበነ፡ ወለተከ፡፡ 
                </ab>
                <ab xml:lang="en">Have you not heard (of it) and have you not seen Susanna? Her father was a king, her mother a queen and her 
                    husband a king. After the death of her husband, kings brought to her father marriage-money for her, gold and silver, and gave same
                    to her father, saying to him: "Give us your daughter". Her father, the king, said to his daughter: "Come, get married". But she 
                    refused and said to her father: "I shall not marry after the death of my husband. I have devoted myself to the Lord, my Creator".
                    Then came slanderous elders and spoke to Susanna: "Come, get married to (one of) us". But she signed her face three times with 
                    the sign of the Lord and said to them: "You are impure and go astray from the Law of the Lord". Then the elders went to her father
                    and said to him: "We saw your daughter fornicating and sinning with everybody". Her father became furious about it and sent his 
                    servants to throw her into a deep [lit. 'big'] pit. When the servants reached her, she prayed to the Lord and the angel Michael 
                    descended near her in the semblance of a man. He spoke to the servants: "Release her and do not throw the woman [into the pit]".
                    [His words] penetrated into their hearts and souls and they said to him: "Be it so. Maybe you can save her". Then they went to her 
                    father. He saw them, while seventy-seven kings were assembled (round him), and the look on the king's face changed. Michael said 
                    to the king: "You have not pondered your deed and have not borne in mind the Lord your God, when you delivered your 
                    handmaid (to be put to death) on account of a false accusation [lit. 'word'] without a fair trial. This is not the way to judge of the 
                    Lord our God. Now do justice to this daughter of yours and let the elders be brought and stand each by himself". Then Michael 
                    arose and said to them: "You elders, where did you see Susanna sinning with her body?". One of them replied: "I saw her under a 
                    fig-tree". One of them said: "I saw her in the palace". One of them said: "I saw her in the women's apartment". And Michael said to 
                    them: "You old witnesses who saw Susanna sinning with her body - may the Lord tear you to pieces - as there are seven divisions 
                    (in the day), at which time (was it)?". But they could not name (the time) to Michael, because their words were lies [lit. 'because of 
                    their lying words'] and their mind was set on (her) destruction. When her father saw this, (he arose) and with him arose the 
                    seventy-seven kings. They prostrated themselves before Susanna and made her a queen above them. She thus earned a double 
                    reward for her faithfulness: queenship on earth and bliss is heaven.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>