<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6995MMDZYohannes" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">Miracle of Mary: Dabra Zamaddo's Abbot Abuna Yohannǝs is transported to Jerusalem</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">199-202</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>After Abuna Bartalomewos died, Mary summoned Abuna Yohannes to leave his country of Gan Amora. Out of his love for Mary, Abuna Yohannes answered Mary’s call for him to set off from his home. Once he was on the road, a thought came to him that he should travel to Jerusalem. That night he slept in a village, where he had found lodging. At midnight, Mary came to Abuna Yohannes, took him to Jerusalem, and showed him all the holy sites there. He woke up back in the village and resumed his journey. He met a poor woman and listened to her views on spiritual matters. Later, he met some monks who were on their way to visit Abba Tatamqa Madhen and joined them. However, the monks were inconsiderate and left Abbuna Yohannes outside while they went in to speak with the head monk. Abba Tatamqa Madhen asked the monks to find Abuna Yohannes, and once they brought him inside, the head monk told him that the poor woman he had met on the road had been Mary in disguise. Mary then came and brought Abuna Yohannes to Dabra Zamaddo, where she installed him as the new abbot.
                    
                    
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1006</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">199-200</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1006</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT6995MMDZYohannes" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT6995MMDZYohannes" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1006"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6995MMDZYohannes" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 123v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ወእምድኅረ፡ ኀለፈ፡ አቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ ተሰይሙ፡ ፭ቱ፡ ኖሎት፡ በዛቲ፡ መካን፡ እምድ[ኅረ]ዝ፡ ጸውዐቶ፡ ወሰሐበቶ፡ በሐብለ፡ ፍቅራ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ለአቡነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ ዐምዳ፡ ወድዳ፡ ለቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ እምነ፡ ሀገሩ፡ ዘይሰመይ፡ ጃን፡ አሞራ፡ ወመላኪሃ፡ ውእቱ፡ በእንተ፡ ፍቅራ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ወበእንተ፡ ፍቅረ፡ ወልዳ፡ ኀዲጎ፡ ኵሎ፡ ፍቅሮ፡ ለዝንቱ፡ ዓለም፡ ወቈሳቍሲሁ፡ ተንሥአ፡ ፍጡነ፡ ከመ፡ ይሑር፡ ኀበ፡ ተጸውዐ፡ ከመ፡ ይርአይ፡ ማኅ ለቅቶ፡ ለነገር፡ ወፍጻሜሁ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">199-200</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013.</note>
                
                <ab>After Abuna Bartalomewos passed away, five shepherds were appointed to this makan. After that, Our Lady Mary sum-moned Abuna Yohannǝs, the pillar and foundation of the church, and drew him with the rope of her love from his country called gan Amora, whose owner he was. For the sake of the love he had for Our Mary and for the sake of the love he had for her Son, he abandoned all the love of this world and its material and stood up quickly to go to where he had been called, to see the end and conclusion of the matter. When he left his country and was travelling on the road, he thought, and the thought which came to him was, “Go to Jerusalem”, came to him. As he was vacillating, he came to a certain village; he lodged there for the night and slept. At midnight, Our Lady came, picked him up and brought him to Jerusalem. She showed him all (the holy) places: (she took him) to the manger, where Our Lord was born; and to (the River) Jordan, where Our Lord was baptized – coming out (of the river, Our Lord) had sat on a rock which was at the bank of the river. She brought him to a place (called) Calvary, where Our Lord was crucified, and to his Golgotha Sepulcher. And she brought him up to Mount of Olive. She fulfilled for him (his wish) in a single night in a spiritual vision. The night was over as he woke up from his sleep and wondered. When morning broke, he resumed his journey. As he was on his journey, he met a certain poor woman. The woman said to him, “Listen to my words, O my brother!” And he said to her – for he was meek and a lover of the poor – “Go on, tell me your concern”. She told him many spiritual matters, and exhorted him. Having heard, he separated himself and resumed his journey. As he walked he met monks who were going to Abba Tatamqa Madhǝn, the righteous and combatant (monk). He, too, went along with them. They arrived at the door of the monk. But Abuna Yohannǝs remained behind by the door to keep the support sticks and foot gears of the monks. Since he was meek and humble, he stayed behind alone to keep others’ possessions. They entered into the house and met with Abba Tatamqa Madhǝn. When they met, Abuna Tatamqa Madhǝn said to them, saying to them, “You have left outside at the door an exalted and honored person”. He said this and ordered them to call him in. They went out and searched. They returned to (Abba Tatamqa Madhǝn) and said to him, “We did search, but we did not find one single person”. As for our father, they ignore him; they did not consider him someone like them because of his small body. He admonished them again, and said to them “Go and call in the righteous and honored one”. They said to him a third time, “There is nobody other than the child who keeps our support sticks”. He said to them, “Call this honored one in”. When Abuna Yohannǝs entered the house, Abuna Tatamqa Madhǝn stood up from afar for the reception of Abuna Yohannǝs. He said to him, “Did you come back safely, O pilgrim of Jerusalem?” He said this and had (this) exhortation to follow: he said to him, “For now, lest you go to Jerusalem, Our Lady Mary has called you to keep the order of her house. And Abuna Bartalomewos has prayed to God that you may keep his tomb. So, today you will not go. What you saw is enough for you. But later you will”. He also told him a secret; he said to him, “Regarding the woman who met you on the road, you should not think she was, or liken her to, one of the worldly poor. Rather, she was Our Lady Mary. Keep everything she told you. For the habit of Our Lady Mary is such when she visits the whole world. When she visits us in order to save us from our enemy, the serpent, one day she would appear in the likeness of the poor and another day she would appear in the likeness of honored people”. After Abuna Tatamqa Madhǝn told him (this), she took him to Dabra Zamaddo where she appointed him and made him the shepherd to the sheep of her house. May the prayer and blessing of Our Lady Mary and the prayer of these shepherds keep us from a sudden death and make us inherit the hall of the Kingdom forever and ever. Amen. </ab> 
                
                
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>