<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6438MartEntawos" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">ገድል፡ ወስምዕ፡ ዘቅዱስ፡ እንጣዎስ፡</title>
                <title xml:lang="gez" type="normalized" corresp="#t1">Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-qǝddus ʾƎnṭāwos</title>
                <title xml:lang="en" type="main" corresp="#t1">Combat and Martyrdom of Saint Antaeus</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="MKr"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness corresp="BLorient686">BL Or. 686 = BLW 257: 60 (1755-69): ff. 277v-281ra (f. 277v: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="BNFabb179">BNA 179: 38 = BNAC 179: 39 = BNACR 163: 40 (1509): ff. 249vc-253vc (f. 249v: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="BAVet264">VVL 264: 13 (1362-63): ff. 74rb-75vb (mutilo) (f. 75r: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML1826">EMML 1826: 23 (XIV-XV s.): ff. 208ra-215rb; EMML "The gadl concludes with a miracle of the saint healing a paralytic [maṣagwee‘] and the martyrdom of Akrāṭes"</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML1827">EMML 1827: 17 (XV s.): ff. 189ra-199rb (f. 189r: 17 Naḥase); EMML 
                    "Enṭāwos became a Christian while he was persecuting the Christians in Damascus. 
                    His life was changed when he, with the other soldeirs of the King, were plundering the church of Theodore the Martyr. The first part of the story is told by the martyr himself"</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML2514">EMML 2514: 46 (1382-88): ff. 223vb-227va (f. 223v: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML6834">EMML 6834: 23 (XIV s.): ff. 165ra-170ra (f. 165r: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    <witness corresp="EMML6951">EMML 6951: 45 (XV s.): ff. 228va-229va (f. 228v: 18 Naḥase)</witness>
                   <witness corresp="Tanasee122"> Ṭānāsee 122 = Dāgā Esṭifānos 11: 23 (XV s.): VIII: 6: ff. 143ra-148rb (f. 143r: 17 Naḥase)</witness>
                    
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p>(from Synaxary version as in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Budge1928Synaxary"/></bibl>)
                    Originally this saint was a wicked man, and knew not Christ, and he devoted all his toil and thought to heap up
                    money. And having arrived in the city of Damascus, he went into the church of Saint
                    Theodore, the man from the East, whilst the congregation was assembled there, now it was
                    the day of their festival, and having entered the church, he set fire to the furniture thereof,
                    and broke the cross. And when he went up into the upper part of the church, he saw with
                    his own eyes fire coming down from heaven in the form of arrows, which transfixed all his
                    soldiers, and one of the arrows pierced his right eye, and he suffered great agony, and the
                    sweat dropped from him. And he cried out from the depth of his heart, and, shedding tears,
                    said, “I believe in Thee, Jesus Christ, Son of the Living God, the God of Saint Theodore,
                    and in the Holy Trinity”; and he pledged himself never again to worship any other [god].
                    Now the Christians, who were celebrating the Offering, did not know what had happened,
                    and when they heard they marveled, and their Faith was increased. And when Saint
                    ‘Entawos (Entaeus) had gone to the bishop, whose name was Elias, he told him everything
                    that had happened, and he asked him to baptize him with Christian baptism. And when the
                    bishop prayed over the water in the vessel for baptism, a pillar of light, like unto the
                    rainbow came down, and all the people saw it. And Saint ‘Entawos (Entaeus) and those
                    who were with him, both Jews and pagans, sixteen hundred and ninety-eight in number,
                    were baptized, and received the Body and Blood of Christ. And Saint ‘Entawos (Entaeus)
                    said, as he marveled at this, “I saw in a dream a shining Lady, and she took me by the hand
                    and led me to the altar, and she brought me near with her hand. And then I went to
                    Jerusalem and I received the Body of Christ. And again I saw on the altar a White Lamb,
                    and having been slain with the knife (?) of the cross, its blood ran into the cup. And when
                    I had partaken of the Body of Christ, the Body became pure bread, and His Blood became
                    wine.” And then, when he was departing from Damascus, the people thereof seized him,
                    and took him to the king. And when the king knew that he was strong in the Faith of
                    Christ, he commanded his soldiers to beat his mouth with clubs (?) until his teeth were
                    broken, and his blood filled his mouth. And then they tied him up in strips of hide for
                    several days, without water and food, and they took him out from them and cast him into a
                    furnace, which was heated with pitch, and sulfur, and bitumen, and fat, and there came
                    forth there from a sweet and pleasant odor. And when the soldiers looked at him they
                    found him standing up in the middle of the fire praying, and they took him to the king.
                    And the king said unto him, “Where didst thou learn the power of magic?” And the saint
                    said unto him, “I know nothing of magic, but [I know] that the might of my Lord Jesus
                    Christ hath put thee to shame.” And being filled with wrath, the king commanded the
                    soldiers to cut off his head with the sword. And when Saint ‘Entawos (Entaeus) stood up
                    facing the East, he stretched out his hands, and committed his soul to God; and as he was
                    praying, a voice came from heaven saying, “Come, My servant, in peace, so that thou
                    mayest rest with George and Stephen.” And when he had finished his prayer the soldiers
                    cut off his head with the sword, and having finished his martyrdom innumerable signs and
                    wonders were made manifest through his body.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Hagiography"/>
                    <term key="Translation"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="MKr" when="2021-04-24">Created entity</change>
            <change when="2022-01-13" who="ES">updated</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT6438MartEntawos" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6438MartEntawos" passive="PRS13397Entawos"/>
                </listRelation>
            </div><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
