<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT6504Mashafa" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Martyrdom of Eusebius of Syria </title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="ES"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness corresp="BLorient686">BL Or. 686 = BLW 257: 38 (1755-69): ff. 150vb-152vb (f. 150v: 13 Yakkātit).</witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Hagiography"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-08">Created entity using the material of Alessandro Bausi</change>
            <change when="2026-01-26" who="ES">Updated following issue https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/2536</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>the text follows the Synaxarion note for 13 Yakkātit as translated by Budge</note>
                <ab>And on this day also died Eusebius the martyr, of splendid glory, and sweet perfume, the
                    son of the judge (or, governor) of Syria; and he had a sister who was full of the spirit, and
                    whose name was Eulophia. This saint was brought up carefully and wisely, and then they
                    betrothed him to a beautiful maiden, the daughter of the Emperor of Rome, and they
                    brought her to his house with great splendor. And on that day he went to his sister, and
                    said unto her, “Counsel me with counsel. Is it better to take a wife, and to live with her [or
                    no]? I do not wish to do this, for I long to renounce the world.” And she said unto him,
                    “What will the taste of this fleeting world benefit thee? It is better for thee to dwell in
                    virginity like Demetrius the Archbishop.” And when the evening had come he went into
                    the bridal-chamber where was the bride, whom they had brought unto him, and he took her
                    head (or, neck) and kissed her, and said unto her, “Prithee, tell me if I may say unto thee a
                    matter.” And she said unto him, “Speak, tell me.” And he made an agreement with her,
                    and he said unto her, “O my sister, know thou that the lust of the world passeth away, and
                    that comeliness and beauty fade, and that nothing whatsoever profiteth a man except the
                    working of righteousness. And now, it is better for us to live as virgins, and not to defile
                    the temples of our bodies of flesh.” And she said unto him, “I agree, O my brother, I do
                    not wish to marry.” And the two of them began to travel together along the path of
                    righteousness, and they dwelt in purity for two years, and they ate no food until [after] they
                    had received the Offering, and they slept in the same bed, and each night they stood in the
                    river, and by day they went into the church, the name whereof is ‘Atra, and each of them
                    made four thousand prostrations, and they read the Psalms of David and the Gospel of
                    John continually. One day the wife of the King of Syria saw Eusebius, and she
                    commanded two of her servants to bring him to her. And when they had brought him,
                    straightway she laid down carpets and purple linen on her bed, and she adorned herself and
                    put round her neck a gold collar, and she said unto Eusebius, “Come [and] sit down, and I
                    will tell thee what is in my heart.” And Eusebius said unto her, “I will not sit down with
                    the wife of the king; tell me what thou hast to say as I stand up.” And she said unto him,
                    “My flesh quivereth, and my bones melt through the greatness of my love for thee; come
                    and sit down with me.” And Eusebius answered and said unto her, “I will not lie with
                    thee. It is not seemly, and the commandment of God is not thus.” And when she wished
                    to lay hold upon him, he went forth, and ran away, and came into the church. And
                    straightway the woman called her servants and said unto them, “As soon as he looked at
                    me with his eyes pain and suffering seized me; he is a magician”; and she commanded
                    fourteen of the elders to make him come out of the church, and to bring him to her. And
                    when they had brought him to her she commanded them to beat him with two iron rods,
                    and to bind him hand and foot and to hang him up on a tree; and they hung him up outside
                    the city, and she sent one of her handmaidens to say unto him, “Consent to do the will of
                    my mistress, that she may have thee taken down”; but he would not hearken unto the voice
                    of the harlot. And straightway he began to pray with the tears running down his face like
                    water in the winter, and he said, “O my Lord God, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob,
                    Who didst command the deliverance of Jacob, and Who didst deliver our fathers from
                    every trial, deliver Thou Thy servant Eusebius, O Thou Who didst deliver Daniel from the
                    mouth of the lion, and Susannah from the hand of the Rabbis, deliver me from the hand of
                    the tyrant and oppressor, for besides Thee I have no other helper.” And then the queen
                    commanded them to strangle him with a cord, and to shoot at him four hundred and sixtyeight arrows; and when they had done this to him, God commanded the angels Michael
                    and Gabriel, and they plucked out the arrows, from his limbs, and he became whole, and
                    there was no injury on him. And when the king came back from his expedition he asked
                    the queen, saying, “What is the offense of Eusebius? And what is his crime that thou hast
                    delivered him over to crucifixion and death?” And his wife the queen said unto him, “I am
                    ashamed to tell thee, for I am afraid of thee”; and the king said, “Speak, tell me, and do not
                    be afraid of me.” And she said unto him, “This man is a magician. He came to me when I
                    was alone, and he asked me [to do] what is unseemly to mention, and when I refused him,
                    he smote me with pains.” And the king commanded the soldiers to take Eusebius down
                    from the tree and to bring him to him. And when they had brought him, the king said unto
                    Eusebius, “Why didst thou meditate evilly the doing of a thing which it is not seemly to do
                    against my wife?” And Eusebius said unto the king, “O my lord, dost thou imagine that
                    these words are true? It is unnecessary to talk about it.” And the king questioned the
                    servants and said unto them, “Is this what I hear true?” And they said unto him, “O my
                    lord the king, when we entered the royal chamber, we found the queen screaming. And
                    when we asked her, ‘What hath happened to thee?’ she told us thus.” And when the king
                    heard this he was filled with anger and fury, like a lion, and he commanded them to cut off
                    the head of Eusebius with the sword, and to cut off his limbs as they cut up an ox, and to
                    throw him into a cauldron, and to smother his mouth with pitch, and to boil him over the
                    fire; [and they did so]. And straightway the archangels Michael and Gabriel came, and
                    they took his body out of the cauldron, and raised him up alive. And after he had risen
                    from the sleep of death, the people found him walking about in the city; and they told the
                    king that he was alive, and he commanded them to bring him to him. And straightway he
                    put four iron bands round him, one round his neck (or, head), one round his body, one
                    round his thighs, and one round his knees, and then they bound him hand and foot, and cast
                    him into the fire. And Michael and Gabriel came and cooled the fire, and Uriel the angel
                    caught him up, and carried him into heaven, where he remained for two years; and then he
                    returned to earth and lived [here] for forty years preaching the Faith; and through him eight
                    thousand and fifty hundred pagans believed. And God made a covenant with him that He
                    would forgive the sins of every one who called upon the name of the saint, or who
                    celebrated his commemoration. </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:CLP46i_may_form_part_of" active="LIT6504Mashafa" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT6504Mashafa" passive="PRS12036Eusebios"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>