<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0034MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's greedy man who did not observe holy days.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">247-248</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>A certain greedy man lived between the two Mount Sehins. He made a lot of money through farming and the relentless acquisition of new land to cultivate. This man never made any offerings to the church. He also refused to observe holy days, and instead spent his time sowing his fields. One year, when his crop was ready to harvest, Mary sent a swarm of locusts. The locusts did not touch any other person’s field, but they did completely decimate this man’s crop. This man also lost all his money, his cattle did not return from the fields, and then his wife died. The man remained lonely and poor into old age, just as Mary had intended.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1036</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">247-248</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1036</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0034MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0034MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1036"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0034MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 145v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ … [በላዕለ፡፩ብእሲ፡] ዘይነብር፡ ማእከለ፡ ፪ኤ፡ ደብረ፡ ስኂን፡ ወመፍቀሬ፡ ንዋይ፡ ውእቱ። እንዘ፡ ንዋዩ፡ ይከውን፡ ብዙኀ፡ ወኢይመስሎ፡ ዘአጥረየ፡ ፩ደ፡ ኅጠተ። ወገራህቱኒ፡ ብዙኅ፡ ኀበ፡ብዙኅ፡ አህጉር፡ ይትጌበር። ወበዝንቱ፡ ፃማሁ፡ ኢያዐርፎሙ፡ ለድኩማን። ወለቤተ፡ ክርስቲያንሂ፡ ኢያወፊ፡ ሕዳጠ፡ ኢመሥዋዕተ፡ ወኢዕጣነ፡ ዘይከውና፡ መድኃኒተ፡ ለነፍሱ። አላ፡ እመ፡ ይረክብ፡ ንዋየ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ይነሥእ፡ ለርእሱ። ወእምብዝኀ፡ ፍቅረ፡ ንዋይ፡ ይሥዕር፡ በዐለ፡ ብሂሎ፡ እረክብ፡ ብዙኀ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">247-248</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked (against a certain man) who lived between the two Mount Sǝhins: He was a lover of money. Although his money was a lot, he never felt that he earned a single seed of grain. Also his farm fields, which he farmed in many countries, were plenty. With this his toil, he did not give respite to the weak. And he never offered to the church even a bit, neither for sacrifice nor incense that would be for the salvation of his soul. To the contrary, if he found any church property, he would take (it) for himself. Because of his too much love for money, he abolished holy days, thinking he would earn plenty. One day, on the holy day of Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, he sowed his farm field. On the holy day of the Holy Trinity, too, he sowed while people told him not to. He again sowed his farm land on the holy day of Our Mother Saint Hannah. He refused and sowed while people told him not to. When harvest time arrived, and when (the grains of) this farm field, too, was ready to be cut, Our Lady brought locust, and the whole country was troubled. They held rogation. The locust left the farm fields of the people of the country because they were not sowed on her holy day. The locust did not devour (anything) but the farm field of the violator. See what Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, had done! In that farm field not (even) gleanings were found. It became as if it were not sown. And also the money in his house was lost, with no fire consuming it or a robber robbing it. And his cattle did not come back from the field to which they went out but were destroyed where they were. After all his property was lost, his wife died, and he remained alone with too much misery. His age of vigor, too, passed away, and he became (too) old. See the power of Our Lady! She allowed the earth to swallow one miser, and she made the other live (long) on the earth to experience devastation and hardship. Since (this man) was a boaster by his might as well as money, she made him remain alone to know his limits, that he was weak. May her prayer and her blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>