<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0025MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's Walatta Nǝgǝst whom the Blessed Virgin saved from a raid by the Arami.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">260-261</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>In Semrata Ab there lived a woman named Walatta Negest, who loved Mary and loyally attended a church built in her name. One day Walatta Negest told Mary that she needed to move to another country. She asked Mary to accompany her on this journey and keep her safe. Unbeknownst to Walatta Negest, the new country was located right next to an Arami community. A few days after she arrived she went out to work the harvest in the farm fields. As she and other Christians were harvesting, the Arami came. The others fled, but Walatta Negest could not run, so she remained with her cattle. The Arami took the cows as booty, but when they tried to take Walatta Negest captive as well, Mary prevented them. The Arami repeatedly returned to the field to capture Walatta Negest, but they never succeeded and finally gave up. Thus was Walatta Negest safe in her new country, and when she eventually returned to Semrata Ab she told the people there all about what Mary had done for her.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1047</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">260-261</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1047</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0025MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0025MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1047"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0025MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 151r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ወሀለወት፡ አሐቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ዘተሐንጸት፡ በስማ፡ … በሀገረ፡ ሥምረተ፡ አብ። ወኀበ፡ ዛቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ሀለወት፡ አሐቲ፡ ብእሲት፡ ዘስማ፡ ወለተ፡ ንግሥት። ወታፈቅራ፡ … ። ወመፍቀሪተ፡ ነዳያን፡ ይእቲ። ወእደዊሃ፡ ፍቱሕ፡ ለውሂብ፡ ዘረከበት። ወገይሠ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያንሂ፡ ኢታፀርዕ፡ መዓልተ፡ ወሌሊተ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">260-261</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>There is a church in the country of sǝmrata Ab built in the name of Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God. At that church there was a woman whose name was Walatta Nǝgǝst. She loved Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God. She was also a lover of the poor. Her hands were open to give whatever she would get. And she never interrupted going to church, day or night. One day, she said to Our Lady, “O My Lady, I need to go to another country to take care of my needs. When I accomplish my desire, I will return here. If your heart consents, go before me and follow me because I have no helper other than you. And I have no other keeper either other than you”. She said this and left for where she thought (to go). The country to which she went was a neighbor of the Arami. And these Arami always fought with the people of the country to which the woman went. A few days after she arrived at that country, she went to (her) farm field because it was harvest season. The people of the country, too, went out with their many cows to harvest the crop. As they were harvesting, the Arami came suddenly and found the Christians with their cattle, unprepared to fight. People fled immediately, but the woman remained with the cattle because she was unable to run. The Arami took the cows as booty. They found (the woman) in the midst the cattle. They left her there and went one mǝʿraf. (Then) they returned to her and stood before her. In order that Our Lady Mary may show her pow- er with this tactic, her power prevented them from taking her captive. And it seemed to them that they had gotten a captive, lest they leave her. Therefore, they returned repeatedly, and the worldly people watched from far as (the Arami) returned to her repeatedly. And they saw the woman standing in the middle of the wide field. The conclusion of the story is that the Arami went to their country. They left her, although they had seen her. The appearance of the woman looked like the cluster of rose fruit and her face shined like the ray of the sun. The Arami left her – although they had seen her – when the power of Our Lady prevented them because she does not forget what one asks her. For she had (asked) her before, saying, “Keep me where I went”. Therefore, she kept her. And the woman came back to her country, and told what Our Lady had done for her – how she saved her from the hand of the Arami. May her prayer and her blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and [ever. Amen].</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>