<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0006MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's people evade the forces of Imam Ahmad Gran</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">207-208</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>Twenty-one years after Abbuna Yohannes received Mary’s message about the coming destruction at the hands of the Arami, the prophecy was at hand. The Arami came and all Christians fled, including those at Dabra Zamaddo. When the Arami reached to the monastery, they wanted to drink from a stream of water that flowed from a cliff to the church. But as the approached the water, Mary made the water flee in the direction of the beta lehem ("house of bread;" i.e., the building where the Eucharist is prepared). The Arami then approached from the opposite direction, but Mary reversed the stream’s flow once again. Finally, the Arami attempted to surround the water, and Mary sent the water in every direction, even suspending some in midair. Unable to drink, the Arami attempted to enter the shrine, but Mary sent insects to bit and sting them. They fled Dabra Zamaddo and did not return. No one entered the shrine again until the years of Arami reign had passed. At that time Mary returned the shrine’s treasures from the places in other countries where they had been taken for safekeeping. The treasures included the Se'ela Adheno (i.e., a sacred icon) as well as three tabots: one of Jesus, one of the Holy Virgin, and one of Abbuna Bartalomewos.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1011</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">207-208</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1011</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0006MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0006MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1011"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0006MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 128r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ወሶበ፡ ኮነ፡ ፳ወ፩፡ዓመተ፡ እምድኅረ፡ አዕረፈ፡ አቡነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ በጽሐ፡ ትንቢቱ፡ ወመጽኡ፡ አረማውያን፡ ወጐዩ፡ ሕዝበ፡ ክርስቲያን። ወበጺሖሙ፡ አረማውያን፡ ኀበ፡ ደብረ፡ ዘመዶ፡ ወበዊኦሙ፡ ውስተ፡ ቅጽራ፡ ነጸርዎ፡ ለማይ፡ ለዘይወርድ፡ እመልዕልተ፡ ጸድፍ፡ መንገለ፡ ጸፍጸፈ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን። ወእምታሕቴሁ፡ ቀርቡ፡ አረማውያን፡ ኀበ፡ ማይ፡ ፈቂዶሙ፡ ለሰትይ። ወጐየ፡ ማይ፡ በማእከለ፡ ጸድፍ፡ መንገለ፡ ቤተ፡ ልሔም። ወተቃደምዎ፡ ውስተ፡ ቤተ፡ ልሔም።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">207-208</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>Twenty-one years after Abuna Yohannǝs rested, his prophecy was at hand. The Arami came and the Christian people fled. When the Arami came to Dabra Zamaddo and entered its fence, they saw the water that streams from the top of the cliff to the pavement of the church. The Arami approached the water from below wanting to drink (it). The water fled in the direction of the beta lǝhem through the middle of the cliff. They surpassed it to the beta lǝhem, and the water returned back through the middle of the cliff and came to the top of the door of the hall. When the Arami saw, they encircled the water, with some of them being by the beta lǝhem and some of them at the top of the fence. It fled from their faces hither and thither. It was also suspended in the sky. The sound of the water was heard, but it did not come down. They did not get a single drop. All this happened so that Our Lady Mary may show her power. She made even the water flee hither and thither. Our Lady Mary did all this to show her power. And when the Arami failed to get the water, they wanted to enter into the shrine. But Our Lady who made the water flee and made it so that they would not get it, sent insects that bite with their teeth and sting with their tails, lest they enter the shrine. She drove them away with such a miracle. After that they did not come back to this place. No one of the Arami or Christians entered (it). It remained closed until the years of the Arami had passed, (and) sǝʿǝla Adhǝno returned from where the people who fled from fear of the Arami had taken it, because they had taken it to another country. The work of Our Lady Mary is amazing. What would it look like if you analyzed it? It is amazing everywhere. She took sǝʿǝla Adhǝno to another country and hid it there from all evil. As for the three tabots, she neither brought them down from their chairs nor brought them out from the shrine. The tabots of God stayed alone. The names of the three tabots are: two of the three are each a tabot of Our Lady Mary [and Jesus]; the small one is of Abuna Bartalomewos; it is the first (to be here). But the two big ones were blessed here. The tabot of Our Lady Mary and the tabot of Jesus are of Abuna Yohannǝs. Ever since they entered into this church, they never left (it) for another country, be it for consecration or fleeing. But the wholly amazing Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, keeps some where they are and saves some where they fled. Everything she does is amazing. The power of her salvation is admired very much. There is no other explanation. May her prayer and petition save us from the traps of our enemy forever and ever. [Amen.]  </ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>