<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0001MMDZYohannes" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">Miracle of Mary: Dabra Zamaddo's Abbot Abuna Yohannǝs and how he opposed the oppressive ruler of Danagaz</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">216-218</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>A posthumous Miracle of Mary. On the feast day of Abbuna Bartalomewos, the people of Danagaz gathered at Dabra Zamaddo to celebrate Mary’s blessings. Traditionally this feast day provided an opportunity for the people gathered to tell the abbot about the hardships they faced. On this day the people of Danagaz spoke to Abbuna Yohannes of their oppressive ruler. Abbuna Yohannes summoned the ruler and asked him to show his people greater kindness. The ruler agreed to do as the abbot said, but when he returned home, the ruler grew angry. He claimed that he would never return to Dabra Zamaddo or be ruled by the abbot there. Hearing of these claims, Abbuna Yohannes consulted with Mary. Mary explained that the ruler had prophesied his own death with these arrogant claims, and she sent “the cup of death” (poison?) to kill the ruler. The narrator then tells of similar events that occurred when a ruler named Gelyanos arrogantly slandered his abbot. As with the ruler of Danagaz, Mary also killed Gelyanos.
                    
                    
                    
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1016</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">216-218</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1016</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0001MMDZYohannes" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0001MMDZYohannes" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1016"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0001MMDZYohannes" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 132r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ በመዋዕሊሁ፡ ለአቡነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ አመ፡ በዐሉ፡ ለአቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ መምህረ፡ ዘመዶ። ሶበ፡ ተጋብኡ፡ ሰብእ፡ በዕለተ፡ ተዝካሩ፡ ለገቢረ፡ በዐል፡ እስመ፡ ተሠርዐ፡ ቅድመ፡ ከመ፡ ይትጋብኡ፡ ሰብእ፡ ለገቢረ፡ በዐል፡ እለ፡ ሀለዉ፡ ታሕተ፡ ምኵናኑ፡ ለአቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ ወእለ፡ ተሰምዩ፡ በሢመተ፡ ዚአሁ፡ ወእም፬ ማዕዘኒሃ፡ ለምድር፡ ይትጋብኡ፡ ሰብእ፡ ከመ፡ ይሳተፉ፡ እምበረከታ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ወላዲተ፡ አምላክ፡ እስመ፡ ይነጽሩ፡ ሥዕላ፡ በዕለተ፡ ዕረፍቱ፡ ለአቡነ፡</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">216-218</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013.</note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Lady Mary worked during the time of Abuna Yohannǝs on the feast day of Abuna Bartalomewos, (the first) abbot of Dabra Zamaddo: People gather together on his memorial day to perform the feast because it was ordered formerly that people who are under the dominion of Abuna Bartalomewos gather together to perform a feast. Those who were appointed under his office and people from the four corners of the land are gathered together to share the blessing of Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, because they watch her icon on the day of rest of Abuna Bartalomewos. For people who are gathered together (for the occasion) find two benefits: one comes from taking refuge with the saints, and the other is they report to the officer the news of their condition, whether or not the ruler rules them with hardship and oppresses them. They would tell him the misfortune inflicted on them. And (the abbot) on his part would pray to Our Lady Mary (on their behalf); and Our Lady would hear him immediately and remove for them their sorrow. Accordingly, the people of Danagaz, who were among the people who gathered together on this feast at the time of Abuna Yohannǝs, reported to the latter the news of their oppression, because the ruler had tormented them very much. When Abuna Yohannǝs heard, he summoned the ruler and asked him to lighten the yoke of the poor. The ruler heard and said to him, “Alright, I will do what you told me. And you will reconcile me with them tomorrow, but today it is already evening; release me to go to my lodging”. When he released him, with this excuse, he left quickly the same night, and arrived at his country in the morning. For he was angry with Abuna Yohannǝs and the poor, saying, “Who of these poor will ever dare to come to my country? For they have accused me (of oppressing them) at the abbot. And which abbot can order me? I will not allow myself to be ruled by the abbots any more. And my feet will not come to this monastery (any more), nor will my eyes see it”. He arrived at his country as he murmured these words and announced (his decision) to the whole country. Those poor people told Abuna Yohannǝs that (the ruler) had left during the night. He said to them, “You, too, go (home)”. They said to him, “Our mind would not even think of it, not to speak of doing to it, (because we know) how the ruler would treat us”. When Abuna Yohannǝs heard, he went to Our Lady and told her the mockery of the ruler, and as the Scripture says, “The prayer of the righteous is capable and empowers”. And Our Lady Mary heard his words immediately. She said to him, “Tell them, ‘Go immediately; do not tarry so that you may see the power of my Son and the power of my miracles given to me.’ For the prophecy of this arrogant ruler has arrived. He has said, ‘I will not come to Dabra Zamaddo anymore.’ For this prophecy of his has been fulfilled for him”. When they heard (this) from Abuna Yohannǝs, they left and arrived at their country in the evening of the same day. They found the people of the country coming together (and) burying him. They arrived and inquired about what happened to him. The people said to them, “He came slandering Abuna Yohannǝs, and, regarding you, counseling with his angel of counsel, the Satan, the father of lies, saying, ‘I shall not let those who accused me at the abbot in my country. Let me see, if the abbot can save them from my servitude.’ He also said, ‘I will not let myself be ruled by an abbot any more. And I will rule people with hardship, if I want. I will make them like the kwahat of the gate of the city. And if I want, I will scatter them, so that they wander in another country. And in regard to Dabra Zamaddo, my eyes shall not see it anymore.’” He arrived as he murmured these words. But before the words of his mouth – false accusation and slander – were finished, sudden death came upon him, because Abuna Yohannǝs had complained to Our Lady Mary against him. And Our Lady Mary, because she knew his demeanor, sent upon him the cup of death to fulfill the words of his prophecy, because he had said with his own mouth, “I shall not see Dabra Zamaddo, and I will not let myself to be ruled by its abbot”. She fulfilled for him what he wished. For there is no servitude for man in flesh after death. He mindlessly prophesized his passing away because he had said, “I shall not see Dabra Zamaddo”. Listen, my brothers! And understand this incident, lest words of arrogance, false accusation and slander come out of your mouth, so what found this violent man will not find you. Gǝlyanos, too, when he showed arrogance toward Basil and Gregory, when he slandered them and appointed for them a day for (their) torture, she sent Mercurius, the martyr of the Son, to requite (Gǝlyanos) with the requital due to his violence and the requital of his arrogance. The same happened against this violent man, too. Because he had been arrogant toward Abuna Yohannǝs and the poor people of his country, she sent on him a sudden death. May her prayer and blessing be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen. </ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>