<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0023MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's leopard that dug out tombs and ate the corpses.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">259</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>During the time when Faqada Krestos served as abbot, there was a period when animals wreaked havoc in the chapel of Takla Haymanot. Every night the priests and monks would close the chapel doors, and in the morning they would remain closed. But inside, they would find that a tomb had been opened, and that the human remains had been taken away to be eaten. A monk named Safane Krestos informed his brothers that he had recently seen a leopard leave the shrine and leap over Takla Haymanot. Abbuna Faqada Krestos decided that the entire community should pray for Mary to help relieve their distress. He recited the prayer “Salama Gabreʾel malʾak," and he instructed the community to continue reciting it for seven days. On the third day of prayer, the people saw the leopard walking around the church. And on the fourth day, the monks found the leopard dead inside the chapel of Ignatius.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1046</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">259</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1046</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0023MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0023MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1046"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0023MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 150v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ … በመዋዕሊሁ፡ ለፈቃደ፡ ክርስቶስ። ሶበ፡ አጽሐቡ፡ አራዊት፡ ወአፍለሱ፡ መቃብረ፡ ወበልዑ፡ ምውታነ፡ በዊኦሙ፡ ውስተ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን። ወሶበ፡ ርእዩ፡ ሰብአ፡ ሀገር፡ ካህናት፡ ወመነኮሳት፡ ወነገርዎ፡ ለአቡሆሙ፡ እንዘ፡ ይብሉ፡ አና ቅጸ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ አጺወነ፡ ነሐውር፡ ምሴተኒ። ወጽባሐኒ፡ ንረክቦሙ፡ በከመ፡ ተአጽዉ፡ ወለመቃብር፡ ንረክቦ፡ ርሕወ፡ ወለሥጋ፡ ሰብእ፡ ይትረከብ፡ ከዊኖ፡ ዘተበትከ። በአይቴ፡ በዊኦ፡ ይበልዕ። ዝንቱ፡ ነገር፡ አጥወቀነ፡ ጥቀ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">259</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked during the time of (abbot) Faqada Krǝstos, when wild animals wrecked havoc, by opening tombs and eating the dead, entering the church: When the people of the country, the priest and monks, noticed, they told their father, saying, “In the evening, we leave having closed the doors of the church; and in the morning we find them still closed. But we find the tomb open, and the human cadaver is found cut off from it. Entering through where does it eat it? This thing has perturbed us very much”. A monk, called Safane Krǝstos, said to them, “One day, as I entered into the church at noon, I saw a leopard exiting from the shrine, jumping over the chapel of Takla Haymanot. It exited and went to the field. When Abuna Faqada Krǝstos heard, he said to his children, “Come, let us pray to Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, with Salama Gabrǝʾel malʾak, because when our ancient fathers were very distressed, they would pray to her with this prayer. And she would listen to them quickly and remove the sorrow in their heart. Therefore, today, too, let us pray to her with this prayer, peradventure she will not ignore us because of the multitude of our sin”. He said this and recited the Salama Gabrǝʾel malʾak with his children seven times. And he ordered the people of the monastery to pray with this prayer seven days. Our Lady is a receiver of the prayer of any one, and is especially definitely partial toward the people of her household. On the third day since this prayer was started, they saw the animal three times in one day, as he went round the church. On the fourth day since this prayer was started, he was found dead inside the chapel of Ignatius. See the miracles of Our Lady, how she hears our prayer and removes our sorrow! You, too, pray to her always so she may rescue us from the waves of this world. May her prayer and her blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>