<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0007MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's three monks who thought of leaving the monastery but survive for months on the spring of honey milk</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">218-220</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>At Dabra Zamaddo there were three monks who piously devoted themselves to prayer. When not tending to monastic duties, these monks labored together to farm their own field. The monks faced many difficulties with their farming, and one year, after sowing the last of their seeds, they decided to move to another country where the farming would be better. But Mary wanted them to remain at her monastery, so she planted the idea in the monks’ minds to spend the night fasting and leave the following day. That night the monks fetched water from the spring that Mary had made bubble up under the feet of Abbuna Bartalomewos. The monks divided the water into gourds, and when they drank it they found that the water had turned into honey. Thus well fed, the monks decided to stay at Dabra Zamaddo for another day. The next day the water turned to honey again, and the monks decided to stay yet longer. This pattern continued for months, keeping the monks at the monastery from Sane to Maskaram. By Maskaram the monks’ field, which they had sown with the last of their seed, had produced perfect ears of corn ready for harvest.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1017</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">218-220</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1017</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0007MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0007MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1017"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0007MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 133r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ተአምር፡ ዘአስተርአየት፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ በውእቱ፡ ማይ፡ ዘአንቅዐቶ፡ እምታሕተ፡ አገሪሁ፡ ለአቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ። አመ፡ አንቅዐቶ፡ ቀዳሚ፡ ኮነ፡ ሕብሩ፡ ጸዐዳ፡ ወጣዕሙኒ፡ ኮነ፡ ከመ፡ ሐሊብ፡ ወሶበ፡ ሰአላ፡ አቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ ወለጠት፡ አርአያሁ፡ ወረሰየቶ፡ ከመ፡ ማይ። ወእምድኅረ፡ አዕረፈ፡ አቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ እምእለ፡ ተጋብኡ፡ ሰብእ፡ በምክንያተ፡ ጽሙና፡ ወእለ፡ ተወከ ሉ፡ በእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ወላዲተ፡ አምላክ፡ ወእለ፡ ተወልዱ፡ እምአቡነ፡ በርተሎሜዎስ፡ በቆብዕ፡ ነበሩ፡ ፫እደው፡ መነኮሳት፡ በተአኅዎ፡ ወበሐብለ፡ ፍቅር።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">218-220</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Lady Mary showed on the water she caused to spring up from under the feet of Abuna Bartalomewos: When she first caused it to spring up, its color was white, and its taste was like milk. When Abuna Bartalomewos prayed to her, she changed its appearance and made it like water. After Abuna Bartalomewos had rested, there were – among the people who came together for silence, who depended on Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, and who were born of Abuna Bartalomewos in cap – three men, monks, who lived in brotherhood and (were bound together) with the rope of love. They did not want the toil of others, but fed on their owen manual work. Their manual work was working the farm field. With this, they were devoted to prayer. And in church, too, they served day and night. Whatever happened, they were never late in lifting incense and the Communion. They were assiduous for Godly work and strangers to vain matters. People never accused them of any evil thing. To the contrary, they praised them with good praise. After they lived in this order for many years, one year, their supply became short. They sowed their farm fields, fighting so many difficulties. When the month of Sane came and their grain was finished, the brothers counseled to go to another country – where there is (good) harvest – and spend the rainy season there. As they set out to go, Our Lady Mary distracted them with an idea, lest they leave on that day, because she did not want their departure because they were her beloved ones and attendants of her house. She brought them an idea and they discussed (it) among themselves. They said, “Let us not go today, because we have eaten yesterday. What would we reply to Our Lord, if we did not spend a night fasting. Today there is, indeed, not a single seed in our abode. So we will spend the night fasting, and tomorrow we shall go where we intended to. It will be proof for us if Our Lord asks us in the mouth of any person, saying, ‘Why did you leave your cell before you spent a night fasting?’ It will be right for us for answering. Let us spend the night fasting. We can go tomorrow”. They spent the day in accordance with this counsel. In the evening, she made them think to fetch water from where she caused it to spring up from under the feet of Abuna Bartalomewos, in order to do her good deed by reason of the water, because Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, thinks of different ideas to save people using many of them. The brothers fetched water from where we mentioned before. She also made them have a thought: they said, “Let us not drink before we measure (it) because it is the property of God”. They said this and poured it in a big gourd, one cup of which would fill a person. When one (of them) tasted it, it was wonderful in his mouth, because Our Lady Mary had made it honeycomb. He finished it with difficulty. For the other two, too, it happened like it did for the first one. When they saw this, they said, “But today we have found dinner that is greater than our normal meal”. On each next day, too, it became similarly honey until the three months (of Kramt) were over, and as the monks said, “We will go tomorrow if we spend this night fasting. But today, we have found dinner that is greater than usual. How can we leave Our Lady when she has not left us? How can we leave her while she feeds us what is better than food? When Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, herself leaves us, when this honey becomes water, at that time we will leave”. As they said, “We will go (the day after) tomorrow rather than tomorrow”, starting with Sane, they came to Maskaram. And their farm field which was sowed was ready (to supply food). It produced perfect ear corn. They cut from the ear corn and brought some home. They roasted it with fire, and ate until they had enough, saying in their heart, “We will drink our honey later”. (But) when they tasted the honey after they had eaten enough from the ear corn, the water returned to its former nature and became (real) water. Look at this miracle which the perfectly admirable Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, had worked! May her prayer and blessing be for us a buffer and shield against this (turbulent) time. And may they save us from the search before her Son, Us, her male and maiden servants, Forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>