<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0036MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's righteous Walda hawaryat and the glory of Mahlet.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">249-250</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>Walda Hawaryat was a loyal follower of Mary. But whereas he read the Mahleta Sege in silence, the other clergy loved to sing it. One day Mary came to Walda Hawaryat and informed him that she would go to the other clergy and strengthen them against exhaustion. Walda Hawaryat asked why Mary would not offer him strength as well. Mary replied that the other clergy needed it more, since when they performed the Mahlet, they sang and danced strenuously. When Mary left to attend to the other clergy, Walda Hawaryat followed her and watched as she handed them instruments and wiped their sweating faces. After witnessing this miracle, Walda Hawaryat decided it was better to sing and dance the Maḫlet with others rather than read it silently, alone.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1038</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">249-250</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1038</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0036MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0036MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1038"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0036MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 146v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ካዕበ፡ ዘአስተርአየቶ፡ … ለወልደ፡ ሐዋርያት፡ እንዘ፡ ውስተ፡ ቤተ፡ መቅደስ፡ ቀዊሞ፡ ቅድመ፡ ታቦት፡ እንዘ፡ ያነብብ፡ ማኅሌተ፡ ጽጌ፡ ወጠኑ፡ ካህናት፡ ዝማሬ፡ ከዊኖሙ፡ ኀበ፡ ዘወትር፡ ምቅዋሞሙ፡ ሶቤሃ፡ ተንሥአት፡ … ወትቤሎ፡ ወልደ፡ ሐዋርያት፡ ሖርኩ፡ ኀበ፡ ውሉድየ፡ እለ፡ ወጠኑ፡ ማኅሌተ፡ ከመ፡ እቁም፡ ምስሌሆሙ፡ ወአጽን ዖሙ፡ እምድካምአስቄጥስ እምኔበው ፡ ቅዱሳን ፡ ዘአስረፉ ፡ እሌ ፡ አልቦሙ ፡ ኀልቊ ። ወይቤላ፡ ወልደ፡ ሐዋርያት፡ እንዘ፡ ዘልፈ፡ እቀውም፡ ቅድ ሜኪ፡ ወአነብብ፡ ውዳሴኪ፡ ለምንት፡ ኢታወሥእኒ፡ ቃለ፡ ወኢታጸንዕኒ፡ እምድ ካም።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">249-250</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>Another miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, revealed to Walda hawaryat: While he was reading the Mahleta tsǝge, standing before the tabot inside the shrine, the clergy started singing from their usual standing place. At that moment, Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, stood up and said to him, “Walda hawaryat, I am going to my sons who have started the mahlet in order to stand with them and strengthen them from their exhaustion”. Walda hawaryat said to her, “Why do you not reply to me a word, nor strengthen me from exhaustion, although I always stand before you and recite your praises? Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, said to him, “Walda hawaryat, do not say so. But you, when you pray, you do so standing in seclusion and in silence. Do you not see how much their toil is?” She said this and went to the clergy who performed the mahlet. Walda hawaryat, too, followed her to see what she was going to do. When he came, he saw her handing them sistrums and the drum. When they sweated she rubbed their faces with her scarf and with her handkerchief. And when the mahlet was fin- ished, she collected the sistrums from their hands. She also brought the drum down from their neck with her hand. After he saw this miracle (Walda hawaryat) loved the mahlet, and honored it in his mind. He became a witness also before others – that singing with the drum and songs is better than glorifying and praising in silence. He, too, kept it firmly for himself. He decided not to pray alone at the time of mahlet, but stood with the clergy who toiled. At the end of his years, he told all people the glory of mahlet, and how Our Lady loves it when they perform it in meekness, void of haughtiness and vain glory. May her prayer and her blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her maidservant Walatta Sara forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>