<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0012MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's church and the three huge boulders that ripped off the cliff and destroyed the roof and walls of the church kitchen</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">221-222</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>Above the church of Mary at Dabra Zamaddo there stood a mountain. One day three large boulders broke off the cliff and came down toward the church. The first boulder missed. The second hit the beta lehem ("house of bread;" i.e., the building where the Eucharist is prepared), causing a wall to collapse and the roof to cave in while clergymen were inside. However, Mary protected the clergymen, saving them and the other buildings from harm. The third boulder thundered toward the shrine just as Abba Baʾamina Egziʾabher was emerging from it. When he saw this, he called out in the names of Abbuna Bartalomewos, Mary, and Jesus Christ, commanding the boulder to stop where it was. The boulder miraculously stopped, suspended in midair.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1018</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">221-222</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1018</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0012MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0012MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1018"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0012MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 134r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ … በደብረ፡ ዘመዶ። ወሀሎ፡ ደብር፡ መልዕልተ፡ ቤታ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም። ወተንሥኡ፡ ፫አእባን፡ ዐቢያን፡ ወተገንጰሉ፡ ወወረዱ፡ መንገለ፡ ቤታ፡ እንዘ፡ ይታለዉ። ወቀዳማዊ፡ ወረደ፡ በፀጋመ፡ ቤተ፡ ልሔም፡ እንዘ፡ ኢያማስን፡ ምንተኒ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">221-222</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked at Dabra Zamaddo: There is a mountain above the church of Our Lady Mary. Three big boulders broke and ripped off and came down in the direction of her church, following each other. The first came down by the left of the beta lǝhem, damaging nothing. But the second hit the beta lǝhem, as the properties of our Lady Mary with which the clergy worked in the beta lǝhem, were in it. When the wall of the beta lǝhem was hit, its side was shattered, with only some of it remaining. Its roof as well as the majority of its wall went way down. The wall was scattered way down. The roof of the house, too, was scattered and crushed. The boulder is the one that is (now) at the gate of the church. O my brothers, see and listen to this miracle which Our Lady Mary works! When the wall of the house was shattered, and when its roof was scattered, not one of the properties of Our Lady Mary in it, with which the clergy worked, was damaged by the strike of the boulder. See this miracle! Are not a wall of a house, built with many stones and much mud, and a roof of a house, of much workmanship, stronger than a (clay) griddle and (clay) jar and all that were made like them? Everything would have perished, if they had not been saved by the power of God. The mighty is not saved by his/its might; and the weak is not destroyed because of his/its weakness, because God keeps him/it with his Bearer, Mary, the redeemer of the world. Compare this matter which Our Lady Mary worked. Although all are her properties, she destroyed the mighty and saved the weak, lest we say, “The mighty is saved by his great might”. And the weak is not destroyed because of his weakness, if he puts his trust in God and in Our Lady Mary, his Bearer. Regarding the third boulder, it followed the (other) two. When its coming was in the direction of the shrine and when Abba Baʾamina Ǝgziʾabher came out of the shrine and saw it bouncing, comeing down, he excommunicated it before it landed and adjured it saying, “By the prayer of Abuna Bartalomewos and by the power of the help of Our Lady Mary, and by the mercy of Our Lord Jesus Christ”, he said to it, “Stop where you are, and do not land”. When the boulder heard the name of its Creator and the name of Our Lady, Bearer of God, before it landed, it stopped (suspended) where it was, not to speak of coming down. Listen, my brothers, how all creatures but humans are servile to their creator! If man were like this boulder, he would have not given up without doing what he thinks. May her prayer and blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son, that stopped the boulder, lest it come down, stop for us the punishment of God, lest it come upon us forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>