<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0013MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's storm that engulfed the country with total darkness for four months.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">231-232</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>In the country of Semrata Ab there lived a monk who fastidiously devoted himself to God and to Mary. During a certain period the people of Semrata Ab experienced much grief, and God responded by covering the earth with a great storm that ruined the grain harvest and washed away farmland. After four months of storms, the monk entered the shrine to pray for Mary to intercede on the people’s behalf and banish the darkness. The monk left the shrine and, looking up at a cloud, cried out: “Be removed!” The cloud immediately disappeared and the sun came out.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1024</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">231-232</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1024</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0013MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0013MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1024"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0013MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 138v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> … ስምዑ፡ ንነግረክሙ፤ ወሀለወት፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ዘተሐንፀት፡ በስማ፡ … በሀገረ፡ ሥምረተ፡ አብ። ወነበረ፡ ፩መነኮስ፡ ውስተ፡ ዛቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ዘኢይወፅእ፡ እምቅጽራ፡ መዐልተ፡ ወሌሊተ፡ ፅሙድ፡ ለተግባረ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ወእሱር፡ በሐብለ፡ ፍቅራ፡ … ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">231-232</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked: Listen as we tell you! There is a church built in the name of Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, in the country of sǝmrata Ab. And there was a certain monk who lived within (the precinct of) this church, who never left the fence day or night. He was devoted to the work of God and bound with the love of Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God. During his time there was too much grief in the world. When God was wrathful at his creatures, he covered the earth with cloud and (torrential) rain until the grain harvest was lost and the entire crop of the farm lands was ruined. When people suffered tribulations exceedingly for about four months, (the monk) went into the shrine and prayed to her quietly, saying to her, “How do you keep silent although you know the weakness of man? Why do you keep silent although you are our intermediator?” He said this and left the shrine with what Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, made him understand. He said to the cloud, “Be removed!” When he said to it, “[Be removed,]” it was removed; the earth brightened and the sun came out. People could not believe it (was the sun) from the moment they saw it until it was dusk. They did not think they knew it before, because the cloud and (the torrential) rain had made them suffer tribulation by want of light and because they had suffered tribulation from cold. Therefore, they did not think that they truly saw the sun, thinking the fog would come back. But the tender-hearted (Mary) removed (it) for them by the prayer of the just, as the Scripture says, “A country is saved by the prayer of a just person”. Therefore, when the monk prayed to Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, she reconciled the world with her Son and removed the destruction. May her prayer and blessing be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen. </ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>