<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0005MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's church and the complaint of the icon for falling on the ground</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">202-204</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>After Abbuna Yohannes had finished constructing the church at Dabra Zamaddo, he placed an icon of Mary on a chair. One day the icon fell off the chair without anyone noticing. Mary went to Abbuna Yohannes directly and asked him about the fallen picture. Abbuna Yohannes instructed a man from his household to go restore the icon to its proper position. At first the man insisted that the icon was already in place, but he followed the abbot’s orders and found that the icon had indeed fallen. He put the image back in place, then returned to Abbuna Yohannes and explained what had happened. The abbot was pleased that the man had told the truth and explained the importance of not telling lies.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1008</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">202-204</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1008</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0005MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0005MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1008"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0005MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 126v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ነገር፡ ዘገብረት፡ ሎቱ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ወተናገረቶ፡ ለአቡነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ እምድኅረ፡ ፈጸመ፡ ሐኒፀ፡ ቤታ፡ ወአንበረ፡ ሥዕላ፡ ውስቴቱ፡ ላዕለ፡ መንበር። ወአሐተ፡ ዕለተ፡ ተደግፈት፡ ውስተ፡ ምድር፡ እንዘ፡ ኢየአምሩ፡ ሰብአ፡ ቤታ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">202-204</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Lady Mary worked for Abuna Yohannǝs and talked with him: After he completed the construction of her church, he placed her icon in it on a chair. One day (the icon) was dropped on the floor without the knowledge of the people of her household. The reason for its dropping was not known. But she went herself to Abuna Yohannǝs and said to him, “How are you sitting on your chair while I am dropped on the floor?” She said this and disappeared from him. When Abuna Yohannǝs heard the words of Our Lady Mary, he called one of the people of his household, and said to him, “Go quickly, pick up My Lady; for she is dropped on the floor”. The person whom he called replied to our father, saying, “She is not dropped, but is in a good position”. But our father said to him, “I say to you, go quickly and pick her up from the floor and place her on her chair”. Then (the messenger) went, and found her dropped on the flour, as our spiritual father had told him. He picked her up and placed her in a good position, as always, and returned to his father. The latter asked him, saying, “How did you find her?” The messenger replied to him, saying, “Yes, I found her dropped (on the floor) as you said”. Our father praised the messenger when he said, “Yes”. He said to him, “You did well that you told me the truth. If you had lied, in the manner in which you earlier said to me, ‘She is not dropped’, I, too, would have considered you a habitual liar. But you did well that you told me the truth. Behold, Our Lady Mary had come and told me, saying to me, ‘How are you sitting on your good chair while I am dropped on the floor?’ She said this and disappeared from me. For my part, I heard her words that she said to me, and obliged you to go and pick her up. And you, you did well that you said to me, ‘Yes’”. See, my brothers, how to lie is a serious offence. For our father had said to the messenger, “If you had belied my words, I, too, would have considered you a habitual liar”. This matter that he taught to the messenger concerns us as well, that we should keep saying “Yes”, and hate lies, in accordance with the words of Our Lord who said in the Gospel, “If people ask you something, say ‘Yes’, if it is true. But if it is not true, say ‘No/It is not.’” O my brother, regarding this “No/It is not”, you should not think that it is a lie, when you see (a mere) statement of “No/It is not”. Nor should you think, furthermore, that Our Lord had taught us (to lie) if you analyze (the statement of) “No/It is not”. “No/It is not” is truth, if said by itself. “No/It is not” is “Yes”, if it is said about what is not/it is not; it is not “No/It is not”. We, too, our brothers, must pursue the truth, and cast away the lie, so that Our Lady Mary may keep us as she kept Abuna Yohannǝs from many traps of Satan. May the prayer and petition of Our Lady Mary dwell in her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. [Amen.].   </ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>