<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0022MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's three adulterous priests who are revealed and defrocked</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">236-238</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>There was a church in Ethiopia where three priests resided, all of whom were serial adulterers. Mary was aware of their sins, and she induced them to confess. On the day of Berhan, the people of the country gathered in the church for mass. While the priests were still in the beta lehem ("house of bread;" i.e., the building where the Eucharist is prepared), they decided that if the people were unable to name their deeds, then they would excommunicate them. The priests announced their ultimatum, and the people, who knew of the priests’ sins, responded by calling out their adultery. Upon hearing this answer, the priests refused to celebrate mass, and they buried the Eucharist in the ground. Astonished, the people brought the priests before the metropolitan, Abbuna Marqos, who immediately demoted the priests. He also severely chastised the people for allowing known sinners to perform the mass. After the people returned home to reconsecrate their church, a thunderbolt came down on the shrine, throwing the clergy to the ground and displacing the Eucharist. When the clergy found the Eucharist, they also discovered the Eucharist the sinful priests had buried. Mary put it into their mind to bring the buried Eucharist to the metropolitan, who broke it into three pieces, keeping two pieces and returning the third.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1028</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">236-238</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1028</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0022MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0022MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1028"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0022MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 140v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>… ስምዑ፡ አኀዊነ፡ ዕጹበ፡ ወመድምመ፡ ዘኮነ። ወነበረት፡ አሐቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ እምአህጉራተ፡ ኢትዮጵያ፡ ዘተሐንጸት፡ በስማ፡ … በመዋዕሊሁ፡ ለጳ ጳስነ፡ አቡነ፡ ማርቆስ። ኀበ፡ ዛቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ዘዘከርናሃ፡ ቅድመ፡ ነበሩ፡ ፫ቀሳውስት፡ ዘይትለአክዋ፡ ለቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን። ለእሉ፡ አዕቀፎሙ፡ ጸላኢ፡ በግብረ፡ ዝሙት። ፩ወለደ፡ ፫ወ፩ወለደ፡ ፪ተ፡ ወሣልሳዊሰ፡ ኢወለደ። ወዘምዎሰ፡ ኢኀደገ። ወእንዘ፡ ይነብሩ፡ በዝንቱ፡ ግብር፡ ከመ፡ አረማዊ፡ ወበ ለፌ፡ ይትበሀሉ፡ ካህናት፡ ወቀዳስያን፡ ወሰብአ፡ ቤታኒ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ይትበሀሉ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">236-238</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>Let us tell you a miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked. Listen, our brothers, to an amazing and wonderful thing that happened! There was a church in one of the countries of Ethiopia built in the name of Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, during the time of our Metropolitan Abuna Marqos. There were three priests who served in the church that we mentioned earlier. The enemy made (these priests) stumble into the act of adultery. (As a result), one begat three children, the second begat two. The third did not, but he did not stop committing adultery. They lived in this deed like an Arami, but on the other hand, they were called priests and Mass celebrants. They were also called people of the household of Our Lady Mary. As for the people of the country, although they knew their (sinful) deeds, there was none, not one, who would say to them, “Why do you do this?” When Our Lady Mary saw that there was no one who was zealous for the law of God, she instigated the sinners themselves to reveal their sin, and she to reveal her miracle on them. (It happened) one day, and the day was the day of Bǝrhan, and the people were gathered in the church (for the occasion). As these sinners were still in the beta lǝhem, and the time to start the celebration of the Mass was at hand, the celebrants spoke to each other, saying, “Unless people tell us our deeds, declaring whether good or bad, we shall not celebrate Mass”. When the people of the country heard the matter, they said to each other, “We do not know the duty of priests, lest we pass judgment on Mass celebrants”. (At this time) the sinners committed transgression publicly, because the enemy had stiffened their heart: they said to the people of the country, “Be excommunicated, if you do not reveal our deeds”. When the people saw and heard that they had excommunicated them, they said, “If you excommunicate us, let us tell you: you have begotten three (children); and you have begotten two (outside marriage); and you are a regular adulterer”. When these sinners heard, they said, “Now that you have told us our deeds, we will not celebrate Mass”. They said this, and buried the Communion in the ground under the altar after it was celebrated. When the people of the country saw the spoilage of the sacrifice, they took (the three priests) to the metropolitan. They came to the metropolitan and told him their concern from the beginning to the end. When the metropolitan heard and knew that what they told him was believable, he demoted (the three) from the rank of priesthood. He next brought up a point, saying, “Why did you keep silent when they sin against God, when it is not ordered in the law that sinners celebrate Mass?” The people of the country said, “What could we do? There is no other priest in our country. Therefore, we kept silent”. The metropolitan said to them, “Cancellation of the Mass is better than sanctification of the body of God in the mouth of sinners”. Furthermore, he said to them, “Have you not heard what the Scripture says, ‘Whoever is adulterous with his body is like one who sacrifices his blood to Satan’. Our Lord, too, has made us understand, saying, ‘Five dogs become one with those which are condemned to be outside’. One of these dogs is the adulterer”. The metropolitan brought them other evidence as well. He said to them, “Now tell me: Was it not because of adultery and merrymaking that (God) was angry in the time of Noah and brought the flood? Was another sin found? And was it not because of adultery that he brought down fire on Sodom in the time of Lot? The flood and fire devastated the world. But God kept the saints, Noah with his children, and Lot with his children, because they did not go along with the sinners. Why did you keep silent when the body of the Creator is oppressed, and the house of his Bearer is called the house of adulterers? It would be hated if an act of adultery was heard even against lay people, not to speak of touching the body of the Creator by the hand of a sinner (and adultery is heard) against priests”. He taught this and said to the people of the country, “Go to your respective homes. Find a priest and (re)consecrate (the church of) Our Lady Mary”. They said to him, “We cannot find one”. And he said to them, “Let her, who has expelled them by their own admission, find one”. When they came back, heaven was torn apart and a thunderbolt came down and rent the roof of the shrine. The clergy were thrown to the ground. Then they later stood up and searched for the Communion. When they searched for it, they found it being two. One (of them) was the one that was prepared for the day, and the other was the one that was buried before – (they were found) the first being on top (of the second). At that time, Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, brought them a thought: They said to each other, “Let us celebrate the Mass with this one, and let the one from earlier stay aside, and let us take it to the metropolitan”. When the metropolitan saw, he admired and wondered. He divided it in three parts. He kept the two parts for himself and the other part he gave to the clergy. The metropolitan said to them, “Know and understand this matter and the miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways Mary, Bearer of God, worked. And hold unto this miracle firmly”. He said this and wrote it down. He ordered the adulterers never to dare touching the body of God. He (ordered) also that people make this miracle a witness like the Book of the Rite. May her prayer and blessing be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>