<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0010MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's icon sǝʿǝla Adhǝno is stolen and returned</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">212-215</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>Once the icon Se'ela Adheno was returned to Dabra Zamaddo, the people of the royal camp sent a thief there to steal the holy image. The thief entered the shrine at night and removed the icon, but Mary directed the man to a field, tied his legs with a rope, and left him there. The next day, a man who was out on his own business entered the field and came upon the tied-up thief and the icon. The people of the country wanted to execute the thief for stealing their beloved icon. However, after hearing Mary’s judgment on the matter, the abbot pardoned him. The narrator then recounts a similar miracle that occurred in Saydnaya, in the house of Marina. A man named Afrengawi had heard about a wondrous icon there that poured forth healing sweat. He went to Marina and, out of his love for Mary, he tried to steal the icon. When he realized he could not to take the whole thing, he attempted to cut the icon in half, and it began to bleed profusely. When others saw the blood on Afrengawi’s clothing, they thought he had killed someone and wanted to execute him. Just as she did with the thief at Dabra Zamaddo, Mary pardoned Afrengawi.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1014</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">212-215</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1014</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0010MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0010MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1014"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0010MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 130v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab> ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ በደብረ፡ ዘመዶ፡ እምድኅረ፡ ተመይጠት፡ ሥዕለ፡ አድኅኖ፡ እምኀበ፡ ተሰደት። ወሶበ፡ ሰምዑ፡ ዜናሃ፡ ሰብአ፡ ትእይንት፡ ወሰብአ፡ ቤተ፡ መንግሥት፡ ከመ፡ ሀለወት፡ ሥዕለ፡ አድኅኖ፡ በደብረ፡ ዘመዶ፡ ዘትገብር፡ መንክረ፡ ወመድምም፡ ለሰሚዖቱ፡ ወሥነ፡ ላሕያኒ፡ መደንግፅ፡ ወመፍርህ፡ ለርእዮቱ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">212-215</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which Our Lady Mary worked at Dabra Zamaddo after sǝʿǝla Adhǝno was returned from where she was exiled: The people of the (royal) camp and the people of the palace heard the news that sǝʿǝla Adhǝno was present at Dabra Zamaddo, working wonders and doing astonishing things to hear, and that the art of its beauty was startling and fearful to see. It is not right to compare it with any icons made by the hand of a human being. I am not sure it was made by the hand of a human being. I think it was rather made by the hand of God. For it is not impossible for God to do this, because he is the bringer of the worlds and the creator of angels (out of nothing). It would not be impossible for God himself to create it, rather than authorize a human being (to paint it). When the people of the (royal) camp heard about this power she worked and how the art of her image was stunning, they sent a thief to steal the miracle- and wonder-working icon of Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, and take it to the camp. The thief came to Dabra Zamaddo and entered the shrine by night. He found sǝʿǝla Adhǝno; he picked it up, carried it, took it out of the shrine and set out through the road he thought was the road that would bring him to the camp. But Our Lady Mary guided him to where she wanted, and brought him to the field where the worldly people assemble on her feast day to watch her icon. People had formed a huge crowd, and (the clergy) entered the church to pray and lift incense, and at that moment, (they noticed that the icon) was missing from its chair. The clergy shouted immediately, and the people of the monastery assembled. They roared and blew the horn. The people of the country heard and all came out and were dispersed to the four corners of the earth, on horses and on foot, wanting to search for it and restore it. At midday, someone went to the field to search for his own concern, not to search for (the icon), but for his own concern. He went to the field which we mentioned earlier, saying, “The worldly people assemble in it on the feast day of Our Lady Mary to watch her icon”. When the man got there, he suddenly (and) unexpectedly found the thief standing and his legs tied with a rope of miracle – which is stronger than iron fetters, although it is not visible to the eye – and carrying the Lady of us all. The man who found the thief shouted. The people of the monastery heard and assembled by him, where the Lady of us all was found. The horn was blown, and there was much jubilation. Mourning was removed and the clergy danced and sang, thanking God and praising the Lady of us all. At that moment, the people of the monastery and the people of the country held counsel to execute (the thief). Some said, “Let us not execute him, but amputate his hands and legs”. And some of them said, “Let us execute him”. But the tender-hearted Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, revealed the judgment to the abbot. The abbot said, “As for us, let us let him go. We did not find him by our search or wisdom. Our Lady Mary, Bearer of God, delivered him into our hands, binding (him) with the rope of miracle. If she wants his execution, executing him is not impossible for her. And if she wants to let him go, she knows (what to do). But on our part, let us let him go wherever he wants”. They decided on this and released him. He went wherever he wanted. Listen, my fathers and brothers! This miracle which the icon of Our Lady showed and the judgment she passed on the thief was not a judgement thieves deserve, but a judgment of peace makers, as the search (for the icon) and theft had happened because of strength of love for her. If we compare this incident, it is similar to what she did at tsaydnāyā and the judgment she passed in favor of the Afrǝngawi. When this Afrǝngawi was in his country and when he travelled for his business, he heard the news about the icon of Our Lady Mary, that it was in tsaydnāyā in the house of Marina (an icon) which works wonders and sheds sweat until it drips on the ground, and with the sweat it heals the entire world. And the art of her appearance was amazing to describe. When (the Afrǝngawi) heard all this news of the icon, he abandoned all the worldly desire in his heart and went quickly to it because his mind had been burnt by her love. He planned to enter their (community) looking like a pilgrim and a way- farer and as if he would live there until the day of his death. He planned this, not to live there but for a cover until he would find a way to steal it and take it to his country. And the people of Martha received him in innocence as it is meet for brothers to receive strangers quickly. They let him live with them in peace. They did not know the guile in his heart – that he came to steal. And the Afrǝngawi did not know that theft was an offence. Rather, he only looked for a way to find (the icon). When he was unable to get it, after he lived there many days, the enemy made him think of another ruse to steal half of its body. He let his hand into an opening of the hedge and cut off with a knife half of its body. At that time, much blood was shed. His hands and clothes were smeared with blood. At that time, when he saw this miracle, he was frightened and shocked. He fled, lest they kill him. As he was fleeing, a man met him and saw that his clothes were smeared with blood. He said to him, “Whom did you kill, was it a righteous man?” The Afrǝngawi said to him, “I did not kill any one, neither righteous nor sinner, but I cut off the icon of our Lady Mary”. The man heard and took him to others. The whole world assembled and counseled to execute him. Our Lady Mary said, “Do not execute him. For what he has done was not with violence and malice. He rather did this because of his much love for me”. Saying so, she let him be left so that they may not execute him. As for the cut off part of her body, she ordered them to join it to where it was cut off. When they joined it to where it was cut off, the piece of the body was glued quickly. The trace of the knife could not be found. But the blood did not fade. It is there, smeared for a sign of where it once was, close to the picture of Our Lady Mary. That which is seen like blood (on the panel), where the picture is, is not paint but blood about which we had heard before. The icon which was in the house of Martha is this same one which is in Dabra Zamaddo. The one that the Afrǝngawi cut off is this icon of Our Lady Mary which is in Dabra Zamaddo. The one that saved the Afrǝngawi, lest they execute him is this same icon of Our Lady Mary which is in Dabra Zamaddo. As we heard before how, in tsaydnāyā, she saved the Afrǝngawi from death, similarly, we saw in Dabra Zamaddo, how she saved the thief. The one in Dabra Zamaddo is that of tsaydnāyā. The one of that time is the same one which is there today, and the one which was cut off is (also) the same one. The piece of body that was glued when they joined it is the same one near the picture of Our Lady Mary. The one that was cut off is the same, and the one that was glued is the same. Look how its body parts are smeared with blood. We brought you this news. Accept it with your ears and put it in your heart. If you believe in Our Lady Mary, that it is possible for her to do all this and you take refuge with her help, you will be saved from all destruction, O worldly man. When Our Lady Mary shows all these miracles, she has no desire that benefits her, but only trust that her power is to save people. May her prayer and blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>