<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0030MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's church and how chewing the body of the Son of the Blessed Virgin is not welcome to the Virgin Mary</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">242-243</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>There was a monk named Timona, to whom Jesus revealed His disappointment in a man named Maba'a Seyon. Jesus had spat on Maba'a Seyon’s clothes so that He, through His spittle, would remain close to the man. But Maba'a Seyon had lent his clothes to others, thwarting Jesus’s plan. Timona called Maba'a Seyon and asked why he lent his clothing to others. Maba'a Seyon claimed that people forced him to give him his clothes. He expressed worry about disappointing Jesus, but Timona brought peace by suggesting that they pray together for His mercy. Mary then approached Timona with a worry of her own, explaining how upset she felt when people chewed on the flesh of her son. Timona asked what the people should do instead, given that Jesus had told them, “Eat my flesh.” Mary responded that the people should not chew the flesh, but rather knead it between tongue and palate. Timona suggested that the priests should make the Eucharist softer and easier to knead in the mouth. That way, if people chewed the flesh it would be a sin of the laity rather than a sin of the clergy.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1032</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">242-243</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1032</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0030MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0030MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1032"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0030MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 143v</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘከሠተት፡ ሎቱ፡ ለ፩መነኰስ፡ ዘስሙ፡ ጢሞና፡ ዘይነብር፡ በሀገረ፡ ምሥራቅ። ወዜነወቶ፡ ሐዘነ፡ ልቡናሃ፡ በከመ፡ ዜነዎ፡ ወልዳ፡ መድኃኔ፡ ዓለም፡ ለውእቱ፡ ጢሞና፡ ሶበ፡ ኀዘነ፡ በመባአ፡ ጽዮን። ወይቤሎ፡ ርኢ፡ ጢሞና፡ ዘገብረ፡ መባአ፡ ጽዮን። ሶበ፡ ነደ፡ ልብየ፡ በፍቅረ፡ ዚአሁ፡ ወረቁ፡ ምራቅየ፡ ውስተ፡ ልብሱ፡ ከመ፡ ኢይትፈለጥ፡ እምኔሁ፡ በመዓልት፡ ወበሌሊት። [ወውእቱ፡ አውሐሶ፡ ለካልእ፡] እስኩ፡ ርእዮ፡ ለዝ፡ ነገር። ሰሚኦ፡ ጢሞና፡ ጸውዖ፡ ለመባ አ፡ ጽዮን። ወይቤሎ፡ ለምንት፡ ታውሕስ፡ ልብስከ፡ ለሰብእ። ናሁ፡ ዜነወኒ፡ እግዚእኒ፡ ሐዘኖ። ወይቤሎ፡ መባአ፡ ጽዮን፡ እወ፡ ገበርኩ፡ ሶበ፡ አገበረኒ፡ ሰብ እ።98 ወዘንተ፡ ብሂሎ፡ ወድቀ፡ ወአንገርገረ፡ ዲበ፡ ምድር። ወይቤ፡ እፎ፡ እከውን፡ እምድኅረዝ፡ እመ፡ ሐዘነ፡ እግዚእየ። ወይቤሎ፡ ጢሞና፡ ኢትቅብጽ፡ ወል ድየ፡ ተስፋ። እስመ፡ እግዚእነ፡ መሐሪ፡ ውእቱ። ባሕቱ፡ ንስአሎ። ወዘንተ፡ ብሂሎ፡ አስተሳለሞሙ፡ ወአዕረቆሙ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">242-243</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>A miracle which (Our Lady) revealed to a certain monk whose name was timona who lived in the country of the east. She informed him of the anguish in her heart, as her Son, the Savior of the World, informed timona when he was disappointed by Mabaʾa tsǝyon. He had said to him, “See, timona, what Mabaʾa tsǝyon has done. When my heart burnt by his love, I spat my spittle on his clothes so that I may not be separated from him day and night. [But he lent his clothes to someone else.] Now see this matter!” timona heard and called Mabaʾa tsǝyon and said to him, “Why do you lend your clothes to others? Behold, the Lord himself has told me his sorrow”. Mabaʾa tsǝyon said to him, “Yes, I have done (so), when people forced me to”. He said this and rolled on the ground. He said to (timona), “What will be of me after this, if my Lord is disappointed with me?” timona said to him, “Do not despond, my son, because Our Lord is merciful. Only let us pray to him”. He said this and made peace between them and reconciled them. Our Lady, too, knowing that timona was a beloved one to her Son, asked him, saying to him, “What should I do, and what will be of me? My mind shivers and my heart melts like wax before fire when people chew the flesh of my Son with their teeth. What shall I do with this my Son? First the Jews crucified him on a wood and pierced him with a spear, and now people chew him with (their) teeth”. timona said to her, “What should people do? Your Son has said, ‘Eat my flesh’, and now you inspire fear in me. What should we do?” Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, said to him, “Let them knead it with their palate and tongue like a grape. Chewing, however, is not right”. Our Lady said this and kept silent. When timona heard, he said, “This sin would be a sin of bishops and priests, if they prepare (the Eucharistic bread) solid like a stone. Let them prepare it soft like a cluster of grapes that would be easy for the palate and tongue to knead. If this is chewed, it would be a sin of the laity”. Hold unto this miracle firmly and keep it in your heart. Do not consider it a fiction and idle talk, because Our Lady does not talk idle, but tells about the life of the soul. May her prayer and blessing and the mercy of her beloved Son be with her servant Gabra Maryam forever and ever. [Amen.]</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>