<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="LIT0033MMDZ" xml:lang="en" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t1">Dabra Zamaddo's man who refused to observe holy days.</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt><p>The record uses data provided by the project <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">The Princeton Ethiopian, Eritrean, and Egyptian Miracles of Mary (PEMM)</ref> </p></editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                    Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                        licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit><witness corresp="EMML6835"></witness></listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">246-247</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>The earliest <ref target="https://pemm.princeton.edu/">PEMM</ref> manuscript in which this story appears is from around 1900. Originally composed in <placeName ref="LOC6431Zammad">Dabra Zamaddo</placeName></creation>
            <abstract>
                <p>There was a man who lived in Wagra Sehin, the city of the saints. Although this man was a Christian in name, in his deeds he strayed from Christian law. Indeed, he followed the lead of the Arami, refusing to fast, pray, or obey the clergy. He mock the Christian religion and demanded that holy day be abolished. On the third day of Genbot (around May 7), a holy day for Mary, the man went to plow the field. At three o’clock a storm suddenly descended and the earth opened up, swallowing the man along with his oxen.</p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2024-05-14">Created entity with the data from https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1035</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl type="translation">
                    <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">246-247</citedRange></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="clavis">
                    <bibl type="PEMM">
                        <ptr type="story" target="bm:PEMM"/>
                        <citedRange unit="item">1035</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listRelation>
                    <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT0033MMDZ" passive="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <relation name="skos:exactMatch" active="LIT0033MMDZ" passive="https://pemm.princeton.edu/stories/1035"></relation>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT0033MMDZ" passive="PRS6819Mary"></relation>
                </listRelation>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="en">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="incipit">
                    <note>Taken from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835, f. 145r</ref>.</note>
                    <ab>ተአምር፡ ዘገብረት፡ … ንነግረክሙ። ወነበረ፡ ፩ብእሲ፡ በመዋዕሊሁ፡ ለዘወልደ፡ ማርያም። ወውእቱ፡ ብእሲ፡ በስምሰ፡ ክርስቲያናዊ፡ ወበግብርሰ፡ ውፁእ፡ እምሕገ፡ ክርስቲ ያን። ወሀገሩኒ፡ ታሕተ፡ ወግረ፡ ስኂን፡ ሀገረ፡ ቅዱሳን፡ እንዘ፡ ይነብር፡ በሀገ ረ፡ ቅዱሳን፡ ኢይሳተፎሙ፡ ለቅዱሳን፡ በግብር፡ አላ፡ ይገብር፡ ግብረ፡ አረሚ። ለጾምኒ፡ ወለጸሎትኒ፡ ኢያአምሮሙ፡ ወለኵሉ፡ ሥርዐተ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ወለካህናትኒ፡ ኢይትኤዘዞሙ። ወሶበ፡ ይብልዎ፡ ዮም፡ ሰንበት፡ ወዮምሰ፡ በዓለ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ኢይደሉ፡ ይትገበሩ፡ ሶበ፡ ይብልዎ፡ ይትቃጸቦሙ።</ab>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <note>Translated by Getatchew Haile in <bibl><ptr target="bm:Getachew2013Voices"/><citedRange unit="page">246-247</citedRange></bibl> from <ref type="mss" corresp="EMML6835">EMML (HMML) 6835</ref>, in 2013. </note>
                
                 
                
                <ab>Let us tell you a miracle which Our Holy Lady, Virgin in two ways, Mary, Bearer of God, worked: There was a certain man during the time of Zawalda Maryam. The man was, indeed, Christian in name, but in deeds he was outside the Christian law. His home country was below Wagra Sǝhin, the city of the saints. Although he lived in the city of the saints, he never participated with the saints in deeds; he rather lived in the deeds of the Arami. He knew neither fast nor prayer nor any order of the church. He did not obey the clergy either. When they said to him, “Today is a holy day” or “Today is the holy day of Our Lady, it is not right to work (on it)” – when they said (so) to him – he would ridicule them. When one day, on 3 Gǝnbot, the holy day of Our Lady’s entrance in the Temple, he went out to work the farm field, the clergy said to him, “It is not right; it is forbidden, lest her holy day be abolished”, he mocked and went out to the field. He spent (most of) the day plowing. At 3 o’clock, (a whirl) wind with a storm rain started. It spun the man (in the air) where he was working and dropped him down with his oxen, as he held the plow in his hand. When he landed on the wide field, the earth opened its mouth and swallowed him up with his oxen. He became the likeness of Dathan and Abiram. See the power of Our Lady which made him like Jezebel, the origin of arrogance, daughter of Beliar, and like Layabo, the blasphemer! O Our Lady, save me, with your prayer and petition from drowning in the sea of sin. And make me do what pleases your Son, And observe silence, the mother of good things. Forever and ever. Amen.</ab>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>