<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="work" xml:lang="en" xml:id="LIT3169Cosmas">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t1">ስምዖሙ፡ ለቆዝሞስ፡ ወዲምያኖስ፡</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t1" type="normalized">Sǝmʿomu la-Qozmos wa-Dimyānos</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t1" type="main">Martyrdom of Cosmas and Damian</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" xml:id="t2"> ቆዝሞስ፡ ወድምያኖስ፡ ወአቢሞስ፡ ለወንድየስ፡ ወአብራንዮስ፡ ወእሞሙ፡ ተውደደ፡</title>
            <title xml:lang="gez" corresp="#t2" type="normalized">Qozmos wa-Dǝmyānos wa-ʾAbimos Lawandyas wa-ʾAbrānyos waʾǝmomu Tawdada</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" corresp="#t2">Cosmas and Damian and Arithmius and Leontius and Abranius and their mother Theodata</title>
            <title xml:lang="en" xml:id="t3ar">Martyrdom of Cosmos and Damian (Arabic version)</title>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
            <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p>
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Work of the literatures of Ethiopia and Eritrea</p>
         </sourceDesc>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness corresp="BLorient686">BL Or. 686 = BLW 257: 19 (1755-69): ff. 67rc-71va (f. 67r: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
                  <witness corresp="BLorient687">BL Or. 687-688 = BLW 258: 21 (XVIII s.): ff. 102va-107r (f. 102v: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="BLorient689">BL Or. 689 = BLW 253: 19 (XV s.): ff. 87vb-94va (f. 87v: 22 Ḫǝdār); 
                  BLW "At the end the names given are <foreign xml:lang="gez">ቆዝሞስ፡ ወድምያኖስ፡ ወአቢሞስ፡ ለወንድየስ፡ ወአብራንዮስ፡ ወእሞሙ፡ ተውደደ።</foreign>"</witness>
               <witness corresp="BLorient691">
                  BL Or. 691 = BLW 255: 12 (XV s.): ff. 179rb-193ra (f. 179rb: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="BNFabb92">
                  BNA 92 = BNAC 92 = BNACR 129: 10 (1509): ff. 130rb-140rb (f. 130rb: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="BNFabb110">
                  BNA 110: 26 = BNAC 110 = BNACR 164: 23 (XVIII s.): ff. 174v-180v (22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML1479">
                  EMML 1479: 23 (1459-60): ff. 137ra-145rb (f. 137r: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML6903">
                  EMML 6903: 24 (XV s.): ff. 125ra-127vb (f. 125r: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML6951">
                  EMML 6951: 17 (XV s.): ff. 76va-83rb (f. 76v: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="EMML6965">
                  EMML 6965: 17 (XIV s.): ff. 82ra-88rb (f. 82r: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="Tanasee121">
                  Ṭānāsee 121 = Dāgā Esṭifānos 10: 14 (1416): A: III: 3: ff. 78ra-83vb (f. 78r: 22 Ḫǝdār)</witness>
               <witness corresp="HamDabraLibanosGS">
                  Dabra Libānos (XV s.) 19.
               </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract><p>(from Synaxary version): These
            saints were natives of the city of Deyoma, in the country of Arabia, and came from the
            temple, which was built in the Name of the Son of God. Their mother was a woman who
            feared God, and she was compassionate and gave large gifts to the pilgrims. After the
            death of their father this widow brought them up and taught them the fear of God. Now
            Cosmas and Damianus having learned practical philosophy (i.e. medicine) used to heal all
            those who were sick without fees and without gifts, and especially those who were poor;
            and their three brothers departed to the desert and became monks. Now Diocletian denied
            Christ because of [the son of] the King of Kuez (Khuzistan), whom he had committed for
            safe keeping to a bishop whose name was Gagyos. Abba Gagyos took an oath to the
            Emperor Diocletian that the son of the King of Kuez (Khuzistan?) had died in his house,
            and that he had buried him with his own hands, [whereas the bishop had connived at the
            prince’s escape]. For this reason Diocletian worshipped foul and brutish idols, and
            commanded all the people who were in his kingdom to worship idols. And certain men
            accused Cosmas and Damianus of preaching in the Name of Christ in every city, and of
            ordering the people not to worship idols. And Diocletian sent letters commanding his
            soldiers to bring them to him, and they did so, and they handed them over to Lasius the
            governor of the city, who tortured them severely with fire, and beat them cruelly with
            whips. Then he asked them questions about their three brothers, and when he knew the
            place where they were, he sent men and they brought them and their mother also with
            them. Then he commanded the soldiers to torture the five of them on the wheel, and they
            did as he commanded. And after this they cast them into a red-hot fiery furnace, and they
            remained therein for three days and three nights and were unharmed. And they also cast
            them into the blazing furnace of the baths, and burned them upon [a red-hot] iron bed, but
            in spite of all these tortures they were not able to overcome them, and God raised them up
            whole and unharmed. When the governor was weary of torturing them, he handed them
            over to the emperor who also tortured them cruelly. And their mother encouraged them to
            endure, and she comforted them and she cursed the emperor to his face and his filthy idols.
            And straightway the emperor commanded the soldiers to cut off her head with the sword,
            and they cut off her head, and she received the crown of martyrdom in the kingdom of the
            heavens. And her body was cast out on the earth and no man dared to bury it. Then
            Cosmas cried out, saying, “O men of this city, is there not among you one man who hath in
            him sufficient mercy to hide the body of this poor old widow and bury it?” And
            straightway Victor, the son of Romanus, came, and he was bold enough to take her body
            and prepare it for the grave and bury it. When the emperor heard that Victor had buried
            her body he was wroth and he commanded his soldiers to drive him into exile in the land
            of Egypt where he received the crown of martyrdom. And as concerning Cosmas and
            Damianus and their brethren the emperor commanded his soldiers to cut off their heads
            with the sword, [and they did so], and they received crowns of martyrdom and life
            everlasting in the kingdom of the heavens. After the days of persecution were ended a
            church was built for them, and God made manifest many signs and wonders [through their
            bodies]. Salutation to the children of Theodata, who are to be praised.</p></abstract>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language></langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
               <term key="Translation"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-07-26">Created XML record from Ethio authority google spreadsheet</change>
         <change who="MV" when="2017-02-27">Added keywords and relation</change>
         <change when="2022-01-07" who="ES">added title variant witnesses relation bibl</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl type="secondary" corresp="#t3ar">
               <bibl><ptr target="bm:Graf1944GCALI"/><citedRange unit="page">508</citedRange></bibl>
               <bibl><ptr target="bm:Graf1944GCALII"/><citedRange unit="page">501</citedRange></bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listRelation>
               <relation name="saws:formsPartOf" active="LIT3169Cosmas" passive="LIT1493Gadlas"/>
               <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT3169Cosmas" passive="PRS3202Cosmas"/>
               <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" active="LIT3169Cosmas" passive="PRS3315Damian"/>      
               <relation name="skos:closeMatch" active="LIT3169Cosmas" passive="NAR0023Qozmos"></relation>
            </listRelation>
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>